<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver to the Call to humiliation: or, A vindication of the Church of England, from the reproaches and objections of W. Woodward, in two fast sermons, preach'd in his conventicle at Lemster, in the county of Hereford, and afterwards published by him.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213077</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825589</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825589</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29975</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25580)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29975)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1754:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver to the Call to humiliation: or, A vindication of the Church of England, from the reproaches and objections of W. Woodward, in two fast sermons, preach'd in his conventicle at Lemster, in the county of Hereford, and afterwards published by him.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30, 39-46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Robinson Junior, book-seller in Ludlow,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Identified on UMI microfilm (Early English books, 1641-1700) reel 1754 as Wing (2nd ed.) A3394A.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Woodward, William, --  Minister of the Gospel. --  Call to humiliation for the grievous sin of persecution --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Persecution --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29975:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29975:1"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO THE <hi>Call to Humiliation:</hi> OR, A VINDICATION OF THE Church of England. From the Reproaches and Objections of <hi>W. Woodward,</hi> in Two Faſt Sermons, Preach'd in his Conventicle at <hi>Lemſter,</hi> in the County of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reford,</hi> and afterwards Publiſhed by him.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Edward Robinſon</hi> Junior, Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller in <hi>Ludlow.</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:29975:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29975:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE <hi>Call to H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MILIATION:</hi> OR, A Vindication of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHEN I firſt met with this importunate <hi>Call to Humiliation,</hi> I wonder'd how it came into the Head of that <hi>Miniſter,</hi> to call upon the <hi>Church of England</hi> in a <hi>Conventicle;</hi> he might as well have call'd upon the <hi>Socinian</hi> Church in <hi>Poland,</hi> or the <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>Penſylvania.</hi> How abſurd was it to ſummon the <hi>Church of England</hi> to the Stool of Repentance in a Presbyterian Aſſembly at <hi>Lemſter,</hi> and to proclaim a Faſt for Perſecution to thoſe whom he pretends were perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by her? But thô the <hi>Church</hi> was out of his Audience, yet it was matter of great Edification to his Hearers, to calumniate and reproach her; and I preſume at the next gathering he was well rewarded for it. See how this Miniſter keeps his Days of <hi>Humiliation;</hi> he Faſts notoriouſly <hi>for Strife and Debate;</hi> inſtead of healing our Wounds, he enlarges and enflames them; he ſets forth the Sufferings of his Diſſenters, with Hyperbole's, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aggravations, to what purpoſe, but to exulcerate and enrage them? as if he were ſent in the <hi>Spirit of Elijah,</hi> he calls in effect for <hi>Fire from Heaven</hi> upon us. The Prophanation of our Faſt Day, was not enough for his Invectives; withal, he could find
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29975:3"/>but little work of <hi>Humiliation</hi> for his own Sectaries, but with loads of Sackcloth and Aſhes he overwhelms our Church, and in a word, he has laid out his whole <hi>Gift</hi> of Calling, and Clamou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and Railing upon it.</p>
            <p>The beſt Apology againſt ſuch a Libel, would be Patience and Silence; and the beſt Anſwer, that which Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> made to certain Reaſons and Raileries of the <hi>Puritans,</hi> to his Reaſons, <hi>No,</hi> and to his Raileries <hi>Nothing.</hi> But there is ſometimes a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of anſwering ſome Perſons <hi>according to their folly;</hi> the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe and triumph with which this <hi>Pamphlet</hi> has been cried up by his followers, the Confidence wherewith they pronounce eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing unanſwerable, that is not anſwer'd; and the Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of<note n="*" place="margin">p. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dumb Dogs,</hi> which this Holy <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> has beſtowed upon us, do make it neceſſary to ſay ſomething in our vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to ſhew how eaſie it is to defend our Church, againſt the feeble Aſſaults of a <hi>Lemſter Conventicle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to his Two Sermons, as he calls them, I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. His Declamations about Perſecution.</item>
                  <item>2. The Reaſons and Objections which he pleads for his Non-conformity.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Days of <hi>Humiliation</hi> are at all times neceſſary to the Church of Chriſt, which, while it is Militant, will be never ſo far without <hi>Spot and Blemiſh,</hi> as not to ſtand in need of publick Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations; but when the Judgments of God, are either imminent, or preſent, and the unbounded wickedneſs of a Nation, do force them down from Heaven, then certainly <hi>is the time to weep, to Sanctify a Faſt, and to call all the Inhabitants of the Land</hi> to a Publick Repentance. Our Church on ſuch occaſions hath content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Self to follow the example of Religious Men in Scripture, and to preſcribe ſuch general Confeſſions, as are univerſally true of all, and particularly, applicable to the Caſe of every one; there is a Confeſſion in that laſt Office, ſo full and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, that no one, who is not much in love with Cavil, can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the inſufficiency of it. But this Miniſter is diſſatisfied with it, he hath ſearched among<note n="*" place="margin">See p. <hi>10, 11.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>accurſed ſtuff,</hi> (as he ſtiles it) of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Affairs,</hi> and after much pains in rummaging,<note n="*" place="margin">See p. <hi>10, 11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>he finds that the accurſed thing</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See p. <hi>10, 11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>lies hid under the covering of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Order, Penal Laws, Laws for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, Subſcriptions; Declarations, Liturgies, Articles, Laws for Ceremonies, and Forms of Prayer.</hi> Thus one whole Conſtitution is <hi>accurſed</hi> in his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29975:3"/>even the <hi>Articles</hi> of our Religion are not excepted, thô ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd by all the Proteſtant Churches, and Seal'd with the Blood of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and the Prayers of all Churches, for at leaſt 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>00 Years together, have been nothing but <hi>Curſes;</hi> and, as <hi>Achan</hi>'s Sacriledge, an <hi>Abomination to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Perſecution is the great <hi>Rock of Offence,</hi> and he is very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at the <hi>Compilers</hi> of the Office, becauſe they have not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd it in the Confeſſion; he cannot forgive a certain<note n="*" place="margin">The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> in particular, who, he thinks, aſſiſted in compoſing the Form, and had before Declar'd, that <hi>Perſecution had not a little contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to fill up the meaſures of the ſins of a Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See his</hi> Ep. Ded. <hi>and</hi> p. 11.</note> and that they who were guilty, <hi>ought ſeriouſly to profeſs their Repentance of it;</hi> But he obſerves, <hi>That he ſaid this before he was a Biſhop,</hi> which is, to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate, that it is no wonder he ſhould now prevaricate, and that he was fall'n from Grace by taking a Biſhoprick on him; But here he had an occaſion of ſhewing his Spight at the Order, and even a <hi>Reconciling Biſhop,</hi> could have no Quarter from him. Now, for once, let Perſecution be as heinous a Sin as he can make it, and let it be granted, that many Church men have been guilty of it; Yet, Why muſt it be particularly confeſs'd in a general Humiliation? Why more than Drunkenneſs, Perjury, Blaſphemy, or Whoredom? Would he have every individual Confeſs, that he has been a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor, a Drunkard, a Blaſphemer, and a Whoremaſter? If many are innocent of theſe Crimes, ſo they are of Perſecution; There are thouſands of <hi>Congregations</hi> that never perſecuted any one, and yet this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Judge</hi> would force them to plead Guilty of it. Be the Sin never ſo <hi>Epidemical,</hi> yet, why ſhould I confeſs it, if I am not Guilty? And as for thoſe that are, let him read over the <hi>Confeſſions,</hi> and he will find, they are in general Expreſſions included in it, and general Confeſſions are ſufficient, becauſe no others can be accommodated to ſo many millions of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> but nothing will pleaſe that <hi>Miniſter,</hi> unleſs the whole Church lye proſtrate at his Feet, and ſubmit to the Diſcipline he impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and then, perhaps, he would think her ſufficiently <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,</hi> and condeſcend to pardon her.</p>
            <p>Let us now reflect a little on the extremity of their Sufferings, as he is pleas'd to repreſent them; and one ſingle Paragraph out of all his <hi>Tragical</hi> Aggravations will be ſufficient. He aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us,<note n="*" place="margin">p. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That it is as clear as the Sun, that for near</hi> 30 <hi>years laſt paſt,</hi> 1600 <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel have ſuffer'd very hard things upon the account of Conſcience, by reaſon of great Fines, and long Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:29975:4"/>At the <hi>Reſtauration</hi> there were many Mininſters ejected who had either intruded themſelves into the <hi>Freeholds</hi> of others, or had <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurp'd</hi> their Benefices in the times of Schiſm and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, without lawful Qualiſications; ſo that they were ejected, not for Conſcience, but Intruſion; whether they were juſt 1600, is not worth enquiry; but that they all ſuffer'd <hi>for Conſcience,</hi> cannot be ſo clear as he pretends, for I ſuppoſe, neither he, nor we can know the Conſciences of 1600, without ſomething of Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; but that all the 1600 <hi>did ſuffer by long Impriſonment,</hi> is an unconſcionable overlaſhing, and <hi>'tis as clear as the Sun,</hi> that it is a notorious Falſhood. He adds, <hi>That many of them have dyed for want of natural Bread, and that both the Shepheards and the Flocks have been ſtarved.</hi> What! Have their Miniſters died with Famine? Have whole <hi>Congregations</hi> periſhed for want of Bread? This is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly all Fiction and <hi>Romance;</hi> or, if you will, the Rhetorick of common beggars, who with doleful Complaints of Starving, cheat the People into Compaſſion. I Grant, <hi>That many Families of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters have been diſtreſs'd by Penal Laws,</hi> thô I think he can never make it out, that they were many thouſands. But the concluſion of this <hi>Tragedy,</hi> is beyond meaſure extravagant. If, <hi>ſays be, the Sufferings of our Brethren were written at large, as the Sufferings of the Saints at other times have been, Mr.</hi> Fox <hi>his</hi> Book of Martyrs, <hi>would be but an Enchiridion in compariſon of it.</hi> That <hi>Work</hi> is an account of the Sufferings of Chriſtians, from the Cruciſixion of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> to the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> and as Volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous as it is, it has not bulk enough for the Diſſenters Sufferings ſince the Reſtauration; nay, it is but a little Epitome in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon. They, alas! have ſuffered more in 30 years, than the whole Church in 1600; and the <hi>Martyrologies</hi> of the whole <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Church, may be infinitely exceeded by the <hi>Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of a few little Conventicles. One would think that many Myriads of Diſſenters had ſuffered Martyrdom; That every in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual Church of <hi>England</hi>-man had deſtroyed as many as <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian;</hi> and that all <hi>England</hi> had been a Sea of Blood for 30 years together; when in the mean time, not one of them ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered death for his Religion, not many of them were ruined in their Eſtates, and pecuniary puniſhments, were the only perſecution of almoſt all of them. Yet he has the Confidence to ſay,<note n="*" place="margin">P. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That the Church of</hi> England <hi>had taken into her hand the Bloody Club of</hi> Cain <hi>to Martyr the Diſſenters;</hi> that his Weapon was a <hi>Club</hi> is revealed to him by<note n="*" place="margin">P. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bucheltzerus,</hi> to whom the <hi>Cabala</hi> was deriv'd; but that the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29975:4"/>Church of <hi>England</hi> has uſed it againſt the Diſſenters, is the revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> for the <hi>Father of Lyes</hi> can be his only Author for it. Let him name but one <hi>Diſſenter</hi> that has been martyr'd by the <hi>Church,</hi> and he ſhall have my Licence to revile her with all the odious Names, from <hi>Coin</hi> to the <hi>Apocalyptick</hi> Whore, in Scripture: But if that be impoſſible, he may ſtill revile, if he pleaſe, but I think he will be no where believed, but in his <hi>Conventicle</hi> and his <hi>Patmos;</hi> ſo the place of his retreat is<note n="*" place="margin">Ep. Ded.</note> called by the fifth <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> that he may be paralell'd to one of the former.</p>
            <p>But this magnifying of Sufferings is an old Artifice of <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> ſo did their Anceſtors the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> as may be ſeen in St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and ſo did the <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> (their late Brethren and Allies,) in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as may be ſeen in <hi>Creſwell</hi>'s <hi>Philopater</hi> and the Books of <hi>Parſons.</hi> Behold how one of them exclaimeth, <hi>Where are now the old Tyrants of the World,</hi> Nero, Decius, Diocle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian, Maxentius, <hi>and the reſt of the great Perſecutors of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? Where is</hi> Genſerick <hi>and</hi> Hunricus, <hi>with their Arrian Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks?</hi> Alluding to the Perſecutions of the <hi>State</hi> here as infinitely beyond them. This was juſt ſuch another Outcry about Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as this Miniſters. And how did the <hi>States-men</hi> of thoſe Times apologize for their Severity?<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See a Treatiſe of the Lord</hi> Burluigh, <hi>Entitled,</hi> The Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Juſtice in <hi>England,</hi> for Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of publick Peace.</note> The ſum of thier defence was this; That what they did was neceſſary to the Preſervation of the <hi>State,</hi> and that their Treaſons and Seditions occaſion'd the hard Laws againſt them. And, Will not the ſame defence ſerve to juſtifie the Laws againſt the <hi>Diſſenters?</hi> The ſevereſt<note n="*" place="margin">As the <hi>1</hi> Eliz. c. <hi>2.23</hi> Eliz. c. <hi>1.35</hi> Eliz. c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Laws, and the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Proceedings againſt them, were in the Time of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> they were then ſuſpended, deprived, impriſon'd, baniſh'd, and ſome of them even<note n="*" place="margin">Barrow <hi>and</hi> Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood.</note> executed, for their ſcandalous Writings; and the ground of theſe Proceedings may be learnt from the Queen her ſelf in the Speech of the Lord Keeper <hi>Puckering</hi> to the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tranſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by Dr. <hi>Pierce</hi> from his own hand Writing, and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in his <hi>Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Mr.</hi> Baxter, an. <hi>1659. p. 109.</hi>
               </note> which was delivered by her Command and Direction: There he tells them, That they were commanded by her <hi>Majeſty,</hi> to give no ear to the <hi>Sollicitations</hi> of the <hi>Puritans,</hi> of whom he declares, <hi>It may be doubted, whether they, or the Jeſuits, do offer more danger, or be more ſpeedily to be repreſſed,</hi> and this Reaſon is there given for it, <hi>becauſe they publiſh, in their Books, and teach in all their Conventicles, ſundry Opinions, not only dangerous to the Realm, but alſo Derogatory to her ſacred Majeſty and her Crown, and by Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of themſelves from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of their fellow Subjects, and by abuſing the ſacred Authority of their Prince, they do joyn with the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits in opening the Door, and preparing the Way, to the</hi> Spaniſh In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29975:5"/>
               <hi>that is threatned againſt the Realm.</hi> Thus far the Queen her ſelf, by the Mouth of her Lord <hi>Keeper;</hi> and ſo effectual was this Speech, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> then paſſed the Act of the 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> the ſevereſt againſt the Diſſenters in the whole Body of our Laws. But a larger account of the true Reaſons of thoſe hard Laws againſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Diſſenters</hi> may be ſeen in a<note n="*" place="margin">It is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at large in Dr. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi>'s <hi>Hiſt. of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</hi> par. <hi>2</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>420.</hi>
               </note> Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Sir <hi>Francis Walſingham</hi> her Secretary, to Monſieur <hi>Chiroy</hi> a Frenchman. The Preſervation of the <hi>State,</hi> againſt their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Practices, is there aſſign'd as the true Cauſe of thoſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities. And as to the <hi>Puritans,</hi> he concludes, that after they had been a great while tolerated; <hi>When they deſended into that vile and baſe Means of Defacing the Government of the Church by ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Paſquils; when they began to make many Subjects in doubt to take Oaths, which is one of the fundamental Points of Juſtice in all Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; when they began both to vaunt of their Strength and Number of their Partizans, and to uſe Comminations, that their Cauſe would prevail through uproar and violence; then it appeared to be no more Deal, no more Canſcience, but meer Faction and Diviſion; and therefore, though the State were compell'd to hold ſomewhat a harder hand to reſtrain them than before, yet was it with as great a moderation, as the Peace of the State or Church could permit.</hi> Such were the Reaſons of the Laws and Proſecutions againſt them in the happy Days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> And have not theſe Obſervations been ſince confirm'd by woful Experience? Is it any wonder, that at the Reſtoration of our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Covernment,</hi> (which had been deſtroy'd by a moſt unjuſtifiable <hi>Rebellion,</hi> when the whole Kingdom had been turn'd into an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> and the beſt of <hi>Kings</hi> was barbarouſly murdered,) the <hi>Law-givers</hi> ſhould look back upon the Miſeries they had felt, and ſecure the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Church,</hi> againſt the increaſe of thoſe <hi>Sectaries</hi> that had ſo lately deſtroy'd them; and yet it is notorious, that theſe Laws were never rigorouſly executed, but when neceſſity requir'd it: Their Aſſemblies were ever tolerated or connived at, when themſelves were pleaſed to ſhew that favour to the Government; but when they began to libel, aſſociate, and plot, againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and it was evident, that the ruin of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> was again attempted; and all the <hi>Sectaries</hi> were ready to contribute their Strength and Power to effect it, was it not then high time for the Government to oppoſe them, to ſecure it ſelf by the Execution of Laws, and to proſecute thoſe who were reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ruin it. They had Liberty enough, till it was made a <hi>Cloak of Maliciouſneſs,</hi> and the Government did never perſecute
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29975:5"/>them, but when it was perſecuted by them. How impertinem then is it to clamour at the <hi>Church,</hi> becauſe the <hi>State</hi> made Laws for its own preſervation; How unjuſt to arraign their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors as Tyrannical, becauſe they would not be deſtroyed; and how impious to call ſuffering for <hi>Sedition;</hi> I erſecution for the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> had any regard to the Judgment of <hi>St.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Aug. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>48.</hi> contra Donat. &amp; Rogat. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi Corrig. Haeret.</note> 
               <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,</hi> it would be to ſome purpoſe to ranſcribe the eſſicacious Reaſons; with which he juſtifies the uſe of Temporal Penalties, for the reducing of <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> but however they may deal with him, the agreement of their chief <hi>Divines,</hi> the declar'd Judgment of their infallible <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and their own undeniable practice, when they had power, will be enough to ſilence and condemn them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Diſſenters</hi> of late have wearied the World with their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries againſt Perſecution, they have magnified Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of Mankind, and cryed it up in their Addreſſes to <hi>K. James,</hi> as the reſtoring of God himſelf to his <hi>Empire;</hi> But nothing in the World that thinks and ſees, can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly believe them; for their own Writings, both paſt and preſent do manifeſtly ſhew, that they never condemn <hi>Perſecution,</hi> but when they cannot <hi>Perſecute.</hi> It may be prov'd by a vaſt cloud of witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, That <hi>Toleration</hi> has been ever damn'd by the <hi>Presbyterians;</hi> and therefore it unavoidably follows, that <hi>Perſecution</hi> has been ever approv'd by them. I could make good this by a deduction from their firſt Apoſtle Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> to their preſent Patriarch Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> but in a Matter ſo notorious, ſo much labour, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary. I appeal to the Teſtimonies of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>They were theſe, Dr.</hi> Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſs, <hi>Mr.</hi> Ward, <hi>Mr.</hi> William Good, <hi>Mr.</hi> Tho. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowgood, <hi>Mr.</hi> Humf. Hardwick, Arthur Salwey, Will. Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar, Geo. Hughes, Edm. Calamy, Tho. Caſe, John Lightfoot, Tho. Watſon. R. Baxter, Tho. Horton, Lazarus Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Matt. Newcomen, Richard Vines, Simeon Aſh; James Crauford, Tho. Edwards.</note> 
               <hi>Twenty</hi> of their moſt eminent <hi>Preachers,</hi> who in the Reign of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> did in their Sermons and Writings, with great Zeal, inveigh againſt <hi>Toleration,</hi> as unlawful in it ſelf, and deſtructive unto Church and State: I refer you likewiſe to a very pathetical Letter <hi>to the Aſſembly,</hi> Subſcribed by all the <hi>London Divines, Ann.</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. wherein they expreſly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their abhorrence of <hi>Toleration,</hi> and exhort the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> to allow no Liberty to the <hi>Independants,</hi> as being notorious Schiſ maticks; and both this <hi>Letter,</hi> and that collection of <hi>Toſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> are to be found in a Pamphlet, Entituled, <hi>Toleration diſprov'd,</hi> which was Printed at <hi>Oxford, Ann.</hi> 1670. But hear the Divines of that Aſſembly it ſelf, expoſtulating with their Diſſenting Brethren the <hi>Independants;</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Papers of Accommodation, cited by <hi>Dr. Still.</hi> in his Sermon about the miſchief of Separation, <hi>p. 41, 42.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>They deſire an Anſwer to this one thing. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome muſt be denied Liberty of their Conſcience in matter of Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29975:6"/>ctice, or none? If none, then ſay they, we muſt renounce our <hi>Covenant,</hi> and let in <hi>Prelacp</hi> again, and all other ways; If a denial of Liberty unto ſome, may be juſt, then <hi>Vniformity</hi> may be ſelted without any Tyranny:</hi> They charge them farther with<note n="*" place="margin">Cited out of the ſame Papers, in his unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of Speara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. <hi>p. 69.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>opening a gap for all Sects to challenge ſuch a Liberty as their due;</hi> And add, <hi>That this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty was denied by the Churches of</hi> New England, <hi>and they have as juſt grounds to deny it as tdey.</hi> Thus we ſee, that not the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> only, but even the new Light of <hi>Independancy</hi> is againſt <hi>Toleration;</hi> and that perſecution of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> was not only their Doctrine, but their Vow and <hi>Covenant</hi> alſo. In that <hi>Covenant</hi> they Swore to <hi>extirpate Prelacy, and to endeavour after <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity in Doctrine, Diſcipline and Worſhip;</hi> and is it not a wonderful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in this <hi>Miniſter,</hi> to Arraign the <hi>Church</hi> for perſecuting, and at the ſame time to contend for the obligation of a perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Covenant,</hi> to reckon <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> among the <hi>accurſed Stuff,</hi> and then Declare that they are bound by <hi>Oath</hi> to ſettle it.</p>
            <p>But their practice at laſt, is the cleareſt demonſtration of their Doctrine. Behold, an<note n="*" place="margin">An Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for putting in execution the Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. 11. 1645.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> againſt the uſe of the <hi>Liturgy; If any perſon hereafter ſhall at any time uſe, or cauſe to be uſed the Book of</hi> Common Prayer <hi>in any Church, or Publick place of Worſhip, or in any Private place or Family within the Kingdom; every perſon ſo offending, for the firſt offence, ſhall pay the ſum of Five, for the Second, Ten pounds, and for the Third, ſhall ſuffer One whole years impriſonment, without Bail or Mainprize.</hi> Do any of our Laws forbid the <hi>diſſenters</hi> to ſerve God in their own <hi>Families,</hi> as they pleaſe? or where is there ſuch an abridgment of Liberty in our <hi>Statute Book?</hi> But yet their proceedings were much more cruel than their Ordinances; ſo far were they from allowing any indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that they would not allow Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience to the Supreme Head and Governor of it; They refuſed to permit their <hi>King</hi> the uſe of the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> in his own Chappel, and infiſted to obtrude the <hi>Directory</hi> upon him againſt his <hi>Conſcience;</hi> ſo that he had reaſon to complain, as he did,<note place="margin">Decl. of <hi>Jun. 18.</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Votes of Nun-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes.</note> of their offering <hi>violence to the Conſcience of their Sovereign,</hi> and to ſay, <hi>If it be Liberty of Conſcience they deſire, he who wants it, is moſt ready to give it.</hi> Nay, thoſe <hi>Prosbyterians,</hi> when they had him in their cuſtody, were ſo inhumane, as to deny him the attendance of ſo much as one <hi>Chaplain</hi> for the performance of Divine offices, thô the Good <hi>King</hi> did often and earneſtly Requeſt it, which (as himſelf obſerves in his<note n="*" place="margin">In his <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Meditations on it) <hi>was a piece of Rigor and Barbariſme, greater, than is ever us'd by Chriſtians, to the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29975:6"/>priſoners, and greateſt malefactors.</hi> Thus it was that they dealt with their <hi>Sovereign;</hi> and the whole Houſhold were Treated no better than the Maſter of it.</p>
            <p>It is known to all the World, how the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Party were plundred, Sequeſtred, Decimated, Impriſoned, and totally Ruin'd by them; With what rigor their rebellious Oaths, Covenants, Engagements and Abjurations were impos'd, and that they were all ejected out of the Churches, Colledges, Schools, and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities. The Lord<note n="*" place="margin">Survey of the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan,</hi> p. <hi>305</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Clarendon</hi> tells us, <hi>That the Reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops who were left alive, and out of priſon being ſtrip'd of all that was their own, preſerved themſelves from Famine, by ſtooping to the loweſt Offices of Teaching Schools, and Officiating in private Families for their Bread, which, together with the Alms of Charitable Perſous, was the only portion of the poor Biſhops, and all the faithful Clergy of the</hi> Church of England.<note n="*" place="margin">His Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. <hi>p. 39.</hi>
               </note> Sir <hi>Henry Yelverton</hi> computes, (and he thought that he was not miſtaken) that <hi>there were</hi> 8000, <hi>who forſook all for the Covenant;</hi> and of an 729 Pariſhes within the Bills of Mortality in <hi>Londom,</hi> 15 were ejected, beſides the Prebends of <hi>St. Pauls</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now it will not be improper to add the Reply of <hi>Arch-Biſhop Bramhal</hi> to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Complaint, That the moſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Godly, Painful and Peaceable Men were ejected, becauſe they durſt not uſe the Ceremonies. <hi>Let Mr.</hi> B. ſays he,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 643. <hi>of his Works.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſum up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one Catalogue, all the Nonconformiſts throughout the Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>ever ſince the beginning of the Reformation, who have been caſt aſide at any time, becauſe they durſt not uſe the Ceremonies; I dare abate him all the reſt of the Kingdom, and only exhibit the Martyrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies of</hi> London, <hi>and the Two <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities; or a Liſt of thoſe, who in theſe late inteſtine Wars, have been impriſon'd and baniſh'd by his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in theſe three places alone, or left to the mercileſs World to beg their Bread, for no other Crime but Loyalty, and becauſe they ſtood affectod to the Ancient Rites and Ceremonies of the</hi> Church of England; <hi>and they ſhall double them for Number, and for Learning, Piety, Induſtry, and the love of Peace, exceed them incomparably.</hi> This is an aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ſhall ſtand unconfuted for ever and let every one now judge between the <hi>Church of England</hi> and the <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> which have been the greateſt Perſecutors.</p>
            <p>Thus have I been forced to retort the accuſation, and to make it good by undeniable Proofs againſt them; that I might ſilence, if poſſible, their Hypocritical Clamours, and convince their Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that they are inexcuſable in Judging that in others, which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29975:7"/>they do themſelves; and that of all men they are the unſitteſt to pull the <hi>Mote</hi> out of the Churches Eye, when the <hi>Beam</hi> is in their own. If Perſecution be the <hi>accurſed Thing,</hi> why have not the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters</hi> themſeves appointed Days of Humiliation for it? Why do they not give it a Place in their Confeſſions? Is it not ſtrange, that, in 40 years time, they ſhould not expreſs their Repentance? And (to uſe this Miniſters Expreſſion,) is it not fit, that <hi>for one Tear of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>they ſhould drop ten, nay, an hundred for one.</hi> It will be objected, that ſome of them, of late years, have condemn'd all Perſecution for Religion; but have they ever kept a <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Humiliation</hi> for it? Do they not think themſelves bound by <hi>Covenant</hi> to extirpate the whole Government of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> And notwithſtanding the Clamours of that Party againſt Perſecution, is it not evident, that where-ever they get Power, they immediately perſecute. We have two Books alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of their Perſecutions in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and when to the extirpation of all the Biſhops, the ruin of Six hundred Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and the Deſolation of four Univerſities, they ſhall add the Deſtruction of the miſerable Reliques of that Church, I will not ſay their Story will be much greater than <hi>Fox</hi>'s <hi>Martyrology,</hi> but I think the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> Sufferings will be but an <hi>Enchiridion</hi> to it. In the mean time we have a fair <hi>Specimen,</hi> however of the modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Party, <hi>whoſe tender Mercies have been always cruel,</hi> and a clear Demonſtration of what may be expected by us, if GOD, in His juſt Judgments, ſhould deliver up our Church unto their Fury. And yet theſe are the men that exclaim againſt <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,</hi> and cry out againſt the Church of <hi>England</hi> as cruel and tyrannical, but let them remember that Reflection, which was long ſince extorted by their Clamours,<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>St.</hi> Serm. on the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par. p. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That they want the Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity of</hi> Adonibezek <hi>to reflect on the Thumbs and Toes; which they have cut off from others, and think themſelves bound to do it again, if it were in their Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after all, this <hi>Miniſter,</hi> though he furiouſly declaims againſt <hi>Perſecution,</hi> and with ſo much Malice and Acrimony arraigns the Church of <hi>England</hi> for it, yet if his invectives be well conſidered, one ſhall find that he no where declares for Liberty of Conſcience, and that no one ought to be perfecuted for his Religion. When he condemns <hi>Perſecution,</hi> he adds always,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See p.</hi> 3, 4, 6, 8, 11.</note> 
               <hi>for the Truth,</hi> which is a plain Intimation, that <hi>Perſecution</hi> for Error he accounts Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; if he really does not, to what purpoſe is that <hi>Limitation?</hi> Why did he not openly condemn all Puniſhments for Conſcience;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29975:7"/>but then he would have condemned the conſtant Doctrine of his Party, and though he was too wary to do that, yet it would have ſpoyl'd the deſign his Sermons, if he had ſpoke out honeſtly, and aſſerted the Lawfulneſs of perſecuting men for their Errors: But if this be his Judgment, (and that Limitation is a ſtrong Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of it,) then the ſum of all is this, That the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> may lawfully perſecute all other <hi>Churches,</hi> but muſt never be perſecuted themſelves by any, becauſe all other <hi>Churches</hi> are erroneous, and the whole <hi>Ineloſure</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> is theirs, and it is only the <hi>Perſecution</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi> that is condemned by them.</p>
            <p>It is evident, that he himſelf founds the Iniquity of the ſevere Proceedings againſt them, upon this ground alone, that they ſuffered <hi>for the Truth.</hi> For to this Objection,<note n="*" place="margin">p. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>the Nonconformiſts have been buffeted for their Faults;</hi> his only Reply is this, <hi>Let's have a fair Hearing before we be judged, the Perſecution of Truth is a great Sin wherever 'tis found;</hi> then he immediately propoſes the Reaſons of their Nonconformity, and concludes at laſt,<note n="*" place="margin">p. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That if in all theſe: Things the Nonconformiſts are in the right, and have witneſſed to the Truth, then ought the Church of</hi> England <hi>to hang down her head,</hi> &amp;c. And thus, as he ſtates the caſe himſelf, if the Diſſenters have not <hi>witneſſed to the Truth,</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not guilty, and all their Outcries about <hi>Perſecution</hi> muſt <hi>paſs for nothing.</hi> Here then lies the ſtreſs of the diſpute, Whether the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> have Truth on their ſide, and were therefore really perſecuted for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs-ſake? I proceed therefore to examine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi> The Reaſons and Objections which he pleads for his Non conformity.</p>
            <p>His firſt Stumbling block is <hi>the Subſcription in the Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, with the Oath in the</hi> Oxford. <hi>Act,</hi> in which are theſe Words, <hi>I. A. B. do declare, That it is unlawful, upon any pretence whatſoever, to take Arms againſt the King: Again I do ſwear, That it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> &amp;c. He adds, <hi>we refuſed thus to declare and ſwear, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires three Things to be obſerved;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>A man may believe a Propoſition to be true, but would not be willing to ſwear it;</hi> and this Objection is a perfect Cavil. He that aſſerts a Propoſition to be true, does mean only that he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of its Truth, and he that ſwears it is true, does only call God to witneſs that he is convinced of it. Nothing is more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious than that in all aſſertory Oaths, when we ſwear to the Truth of Things, we are underſtood to declare no more than our own Belief and Knowledge concerning them; and thus, when I ſwear
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29975:8"/>that it is unlawful to reſiſt, nothing more can be underſtood, than that I am fully ſatisfied of it; if I believe it unlawful, I may <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe</hi> and <hi>declare</hi> that it is ſo, and if I cam do that, I may alſo ſwear it, ſince in this Caſe an <hi>Oath,</hi> ſuperadded to a <hi>Declaration,</hi> muſt follow the nature of the <hi>Principal,</hi> and can be nothing elſe but a Sacred Confirmation of my ſincerity in declaring; and I am mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally certain, that no <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> in <hi>England</hi> would have refuſed to adminiſter the <hi>Oath</hi> with this Interpretation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he objects, <hi>that</hi> Barclay, Grotius, <hi>and others who have written in favour of Kings, do yet allow ſome Caſes, in which it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to reſiſt them, and if a King does govern by his Will, and not by Law, he doth</hi> excidere de jure, that is, <hi>he forfeits his Right to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern.</hi> I anſwer, that an Arbitrary King does forfeit his Right, is affirmed by neither of theſe Authors, but is contradicted by them; and though it be true, that <hi>Barelay, Grotius,</hi> and others, whether <hi>Republicans, Jeſuits,</hi> or <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> have allowed Exceptions for reſiſting, yet I am ſure the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> has made none in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; they that reſiſt ſhall receive Damnation,</hi> is denounced without any <hi>Limitation,</hi> and how ſhall we limit, where GOD hath not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited, or diſtinguiſh, where He hath not diſtinguiſhed. So was the Rule underſtood and practiced by the firſt and beſt of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſo was it taught by the firſt Reformers of our Church, and ſome of them with their Blood bore witneſs to it. The <hi>Popes</hi> were the firſt Chriſtians that taught Reſiſtance, but though an <hi>Augel</hi> from Heaven had taught it, we have received another Doctrine, and could not have departed from it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he adds, <hi>That all the Nobility and Gentry of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>and all the Proteſtant Princes beyond Sea, in their Proceedings againſt King</hi> James, <hi>have juſtified the Nonconformiſts in refuſing the Oath.</hi> Now I have no Correſpondence with all theſe <hi>Princes, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> and therefore know not their minds about it, but I am ſure he cannot make good his <hi>all</hi> without taking Sanctuary in Hyperbole. There be many that think thoſe <hi>Proceedings</hi> may be juſtified without juſtifying Reſiſtance, but I believe there are no <hi>Princes</hi> that will allow it againſt themſelves, and if the Majority of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> do juſtifie what they once condemn'd, their Authority can be urged on neither ſide, and though there he a <hi>Revolution</hi> of Opinions as well as Governments, yet the nature of Things is immutable, and Truth <hi>the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:29975:8"/>
            <p>His Second ſcruple is about Reordination, <hi>as tho' Ordination by Presbyters were not ſufficient, without the laying on of the hands of thoſe, we now call Biſhops.</hi> But firſt, ſince this <hi>Miniſter</hi> hath now undertaken to argue, he ſhould have prov'd, that <hi>Reor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> implys a <hi>Nullity</hi> of their former Orders; But, as no <hi>Declaration</hi> of their inſufficiency is requir'd, ſo, neither is it imply'd in the nature of the thing, nor underſtood to be ſo by <hi>Conſtruction</hi> of the Fact, as appears from the <hi>Reordination</hi> of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>French Miniſters,</hi> whoſe Orders have never been condemned by our Church, who never intended to renource them by that Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor are ſuppoſed to do ſo. <hi>Secondly,</hi> tho' the Ordination of <hi>Presbyters</hi> be granted to be ſufficient, yet this will not juſtify the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> Ordinations; There is all evidnet difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Caſe of theſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> and the <hi>Presbyters</hi> of ſome <hi>Foreign Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe Foreign Divines, tho' their Churches are not under <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Government, yet they do not ſeparate from <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Communion, but have all own'd Commun on with the <hi>Church of England. Blondel,</hi> their beſt Advocate for Presbyterian Parity, does yet condemn Separation from Biſhop; as <hi>Schiſmatical,</hi> and expreſly<note n="*" place="margin">Praef. ad Apol. <hi>p.</hi> 59.</note> declares, that <hi>Aerius</hi> was therefore an <hi>Heretick,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he aſſerted, <hi>That ſeparation was to be made from thoſe who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any difference between Biſhops and Presbyters.</hi> But their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving of <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Government, and coadmning Separation from it as <hi>Schiſmatical,</hi> has been ſo often, ſo irrefragably<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid <hi>p. 47</hi> and <hi>Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to affirm the Biſhop of <hi>Chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, p. 164</hi> of his Works.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that there can be no longer any Controverſie about it. But on the other ſide, the preſent Nonconformiſts do make <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Government the chief reaſon of their <hi>Separation,</hi> and condemn it as unlawful and <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> which no Reſormed <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> that we know, did ever before them; and this is certainly a very material difference between them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Ordination of <hi>Presbyters</hi> withou: <hi>Biſhops</hi> in thoſe Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Churches, has been generally defended by the plea of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity;</hi> thus it has been defended by ſome of the Foreign<note n="†" place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi>'s, and <hi>Mortons</hi> Bcoks in defence of Eiſcopacy, Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall</hi> in his <hi>Sup.</hi> Dr. <hi>Durell</hi>'s <hi>Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical</hi> and <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and lately in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Foreign, reformed Divines.</note> 
               <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> themſelves, and thus by many<note n="*" place="margin">As <hi>Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Field, Andrews,</hi> and leately by Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi> in his Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the defence of Dr. <hi>Still.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Divines</hi> of our own <hi>Church.</hi> As their circumſtances were, it was impoſſible for them to have <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and therefore they wanted them out of invincible <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity;</hi> whereas our <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are uncapal le of that Plea, they reject the Authority of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and Ordain in oppoſition to them, and therefore it is evident, they are under no neceſſity, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently their Orders may be thought in ufficient, without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaching
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29975:9"/>the validity of Foreign Ordinations; And thus having ſeparated their Cauſe, from that of other <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> I proceed to examine what he urges for it, and his firſt Reaſon is this;</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>That the word of God makes not difference between the</hi> Biſhop <hi>and the</hi> Presbyter, <hi>or Paſtor of a Church,</hi> and he cites thoſe Texts, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7.28. and <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7. to prove that thoſe, Names are promiſcuouſly uſed. Three ways have been taken to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer this Objection; 1. That both the Names of <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> in Scripture, denote always the Prelatical <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and not the Modern <hi>Presbyter.</hi> 2. That even in Scripture, the Names are ſo diſtinguiſhed, that a mere <hi>Presbyter</hi> alone is never call'd a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> tho' a <hi>Biſhop</hi> is often call'd a <hi>Presbyter.</hi> Both theſe Opinions have been well defended<note n="*" place="margin">By Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> and Dr. <hi>Taylor.</hi>
               </note>, and perhaps, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to conſute them; but to cut off all ſuperfluous Diſputes, it is enough to Anſwer, 3. That tho' the Names of <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> are not diſtinct in Scripture; yet it is a very fallacious way of arguing from the indiſtinction of <hi>Names;</hi> to infer the Identity of <hi>Offices. St. John</hi> the Apoſtle calls himſelf twice a<note n="*" place="margin">2d <hi>Ep.</hi> John <hi>v.</hi> 1. 3d <hi>Ep. v.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Rom. 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>Andronious Junia,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>Epapheaditus,</hi> (who according to this Miniſter's opinion, were only Presbyters,) are reciprocally call'd <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> Are the <hi>Offices</hi> of an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> therefore really the ſame? This one inſtance is a clear Demonſtration of the Falſhood of that Conſequence. Though there was a confuſion of Names, there was yet, a diſtinction of Offices, and if that can be proved, <hi>viz. That in the Apoſtolical Churches, ſome ſingle Perſons had a Pre-eminency of Power and Authority over the other Presbyters,</hi> it will neceſſarily follow, that that Office, (to which the Name of Biſhops is now appropriated,) is at leaſt of <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Jus Divinum Miniſterii Anglicani, <hi>p.</hi> 71, 72.</note> are granted by all ſides to have had ſuch a Superiority; and the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> only pretend that their Office was <hi>extraordinary,</hi> and expired with them; but this is affirmed without ſufficient Proof, for what, though <hi>Timothy</hi> be required to do the Work of an Evangeliſt, can they prove that this ſignifies any more than a Preacher of the Goſpel? And if it could be proved to be a Temporary Office, how does it appear that his Epiſcopal Power was a part of that Office, or that it was not diſtinct and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from it? On the contrary it may be proved, by <hi>a Cloud of Witneſſes,</hi> that this Power was not Temporary, but was every where derived by Succeſſion upon ſingle Perſons; and particulably: as to the Succeſſion of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> we have the Confeſſion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29975:9"/>of <hi>Du Moulin,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In his 3d. Ep. to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> p. <hi>181, 182.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That the Epiſcopal Order was (of Apoſtolical inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion)—and that what name ſoever we give to</hi> Timothy <hi>and</hi> Titus, <hi>whether Biſhops or Evangeliſts, it is manife that they had Biſhops for their Succeſſors and Heirs of their pre-eminency.</hi>) And in fine, this precarious Pretence of extraordinary Offices may with equal rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be urg'd, (as we find it is by <hi>Anabaptiſts; Quakers</hi> and <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>) againſt the whole Order of the Miniſtry; and if it be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted (as Mr.<note n="*" place="margin">In his <hi>Chriſtian Directory,</hi> cited in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſon. of Separ. p. <hi>264.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baxter</hi> once confeſs'd) <hi>we leave room for andaecious Wits, to queſtion other Goſpel Inſtitutions, at Paſtors and Sacraments, and to ſay they were but for one Age.</hi> The Sum is this, there is clear Evldence in Scripture, that there were ſome Officers who had Power of Juriſdiction over Presbyters, and therefore the Texts which he produces to ſhew the Community of Names can be no Argument againſt it.</p>
            <p>But to juſtifie Ordination by Presbyter, he cites, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. where it is intimated that <hi>Timothy</hi> was ordained by the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery. To this it is anſwered<note n="*" place="margin">On the brief Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in Anſwer to the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, p. <hi>195.</hi> &amp;c.</note>. 1. That <hi>Presbytery</hi> there is taken for the <hi>Office</hi> of a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and ſo the Senſe runs thus, <hi>neglect not the Gift, or Office of a Presbyter which was given thee by Prophecy with the Impoſition of hands;</hi> and this Senſe is warranted by the Authority of<note n="*" place="margin">Calv. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. lib. 4. c. 3. ſect. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin,</hi> and of St.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>St</hi> Jerom. <hi>in</hi> Locum.</note> 
               <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> long before him. 2. If <hi>Presbytery</hi> be taken for the <hi>Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners:</hi> it may nevertheleſs be underſtood of ſuch Presbyters as had a <hi>Superior Power</hi> over others, for as Apoſtles and Biſhops are ſometimes called Presbyters, ſo might they Collectively be called <hi>Presbytery;</hi> and accordingly it is obſerved, that the Apoſtles themſelves are called by St <hi>Ignatius, the Presbytery of the Church.</hi> 3. It is evident from 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was the principal, if not the only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ordainer of him, and ſurely it is no good conſequence, that if Presbyters may aſſiſt an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> or a <hi>Biſhop</hi> at an Ordmation, therefore they may ordain without him. He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chides, that <hi>Auguſtine, Jerome,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> with many other <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Latins,</hi> are of his Judgment, but he produces no paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages out of any of theſe Authours, but aſſerts roundly, that they are all of his mind, and 'tis as eaſie to anſwer, that they are all againſt him; however, when he ſhall produce his Teſtimonies, it will be time enough to examine them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He proceeds to juſtifie his Orders by the Authority of our own and Foreign Churches, <hi>All our learned Divines at the Reformation from Popery, beld that Ordination by the Paſtors of Churches</hi> (he means Presbyters) <hi>was valid and good.</hi> Thus he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29975:10"/>affirms on, without proving, <hi>many</hi> Greeks <hi>and</hi> Latines <hi>and all our Divines,</hi> are only conſident Phraſes and ought to paſs for nothing; in ſhort I defie him to produce any one of thoſe Divines, that has allowed of Presbyterian Ordinations made in a Schiſmatical oppoſition to Biſhops, and without the Caſe of neceſſity. But he adds, <hi>The Twenty third Article of Miniſtring in the Congregation, ſeems to ſpeak as much;</hi> That Article declares, <hi>That it is not lawful to exerciſe the Miniſtry without a lawful Calling, and that thoſe are lawfully called, who are called by Men, who have publick Authority given them in the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Quibus poteſtas publice conceſſa eſt <hi>in</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Art. Edit. 1552 &amp; 1562.</note> 
               <hi>Congnegation,</hi> i.e. the Church to do it. And how impertinent is this Allegation? <hi>was publick Authority ever given in our Church</hi> to Presbyters, to ordain Prieſts or Deacons? on the contrary, it is expreſſy provided in the Preface to the<note n="*" place="margin">Approved <hi>Art. 36.</hi> and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Acts of Parl. <hi>Reg. Edw. 6. &amp; Eliz.</hi> p. <hi>58.</hi>
               </note> Form of Ordination in our Liturgy, that <hi>whereas it is evident unto all Men diligently reading Holy Scripture and ancient Authors, that from the Apoſtles time there hath been theſe Orders of Miniſters in Chriſts Church, Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons—therefore to the intent theſe Orders ſhould be continued, and reverently uſed and eſteemed in the Church of</hi> England; <hi>it is requiſite, that no Man ſhall execute any of them, excep the be called, tryed, examined, and admitted according to the Form hereafter following;</hi> and I hope it is evident from that form, that a Biſhop is neceſſary to Ordination.</p>
            <p>He goes on and affirms, <hi>That the</hi> French, Belgick <hi>and</hi> Helvetick <hi>Churches, beſides many others, are of his Judgment.</hi> All the <hi>other Proteſtant Churches</hi> (excepting only <hi>Geneva</hi>) have <hi>Epiſoopal</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that they allow Ordination by Presbyters in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to it, is an Aſſertion that may well be thought incredible, till it be ſufficiently proved; and as for the Churches he menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, their <hi>Divines</hi> account the <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> Ordinations <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical,</hi> and the beſt defence of their own is <hi>neceſſity.</hi> But <hi>he needs not name the Church of</hi> Scotland, <hi>for</hi> Scotland, (ſays he) <hi>hath juſtified all our Non-Conformity.</hi> By <hi>Scotland</hi> he means the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian party of that Kingdom,<note n="*" place="margin">See the Letters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> p. <hi>58.</hi>
               </note> the leſſer part for the whole; but however, if <hi>Scotland</hi> juſtifies them, it is the only Church in the world that do ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> He adds, <hi>our Dioceſan Biſhops may glory over us, as the Kings Biſhops, or Biſhops of the State,</hi> which is juſt the Raillery of the Papiſts, <hi>Parliament Biſhops, and Nags-head Biſhops.</hi> But are our Biſhops ordained by the King and State? are they not Chriſt's Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and Scripture Biſhops? No, for this new Apoſtle of <hi>Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> does Peremptorily tell them, <hi>that they muſt not pretend to be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29975:10"/>ſo near in Blood to the Scripture Biſhops of the firſt Two hundred years as the Paſtors of ſingle Congregations.</hi> But with Submiſſion to his Apoſtleſhip, I reply, that the<note n="*" place="margin">Jus Divin. Miniſ. Aug. 71.</note> Presbyterian Aſſembly have granted, that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> had ſuper out Authority over Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and therefore our Biſhops having the ſame Authority, may pretend to <hi>Kindred</hi> with them. 2.<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>p.</hi> 140.</note> They acknowledge alſo after <hi>Blondel,</hi> that above 140 years after Chriſt, Biſhops were ſet over Presbyters; ſo that they grant them to be introduced with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 40 or 50 years after the deceaſe of all the Apoſtles. 3. The Epiſtles of <hi>Ignatius</hi> (who was <hi>Contemporary</hi> with the Apoſtles, and ſuffered Martyrdom within nine years after the deceaſe of St. <hi>John</hi>) do manifeſtly ſhew; that the ſuperiour Authority of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops was then eſtabliſhed in the Church, and therefore certainly by <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Inſtitution. And the Authority of theſe Epiſtles has been ſo demonſtratively cleared from all Exceptions by <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Pearſon,</hi> that there is now no Contreverſie about it. 4. Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> at the end of his Book, has plainly demonſtrated the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Inſtitution of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and he Sums up his <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> in theſe Words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epiſcopal Government is acknowledged to have been received univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally in the Church, preſently after the Apoſtles times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Between the Apoſtles times, and this preſently after, there was not time enough for, nor poſſibility of ſo great an Alteration;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And therefore, there was no ſuch Alterat on as is pretended. And therefore, Epiſcopacy being</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>By</hi> Peter du Moulin, Beza. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mier Nic. vedetius, <hi>whom he cites as Confeſſing it.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>confeſſed to be ſo Antient and Catholick, muſt be granted alſo to be Apoſtolick.</hi> Quod erat Demonſtrandum.</p>
            <p>And I hope this Miniſter will condeſcend to anſwer this <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration,</hi> when he writes again, or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wever be ſo modeſt, as not to conclude ſo confidently, when he has proved nothing. But behold the Chair of Infallibility! <hi>Wherefore I ſay, that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by the hands of the Paſtors of Churches, filled with the Holy Ghoſt, is much more elegible than by Dioceſan Biſhops;</hi> a very pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory Decree, but we muſt not queſtion it, for <hi>Pythagoras</hi> hath ſaid ſo; yet thus much I preſume to Anſwer, that Dioceſan Biſhops are filled with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as well as parochal Paſtors, and that <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> have no Title to it.</p>
            <p>We come now to his Third Reaſon of Non-Conformity, <hi>the Declaration of Aſſent and Conſent, required in the Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity to the Book of Common-Prayes.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> He can't Aſſent to that paſſage
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29975:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the <hi>Athanaſian Creed,</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>that every one that doth not keep that Faith whole, ſhall without doubt periſh Everlaſtingly.</hi> Now it is certain, the <hi>Athanaſian Creed</hi> is entirely<note n="*" place="margin">The Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Foreign Reformed Churches, p. <hi>32, 33.</hi>
               </note> received, and approved by all the proteſtant Churches in the World, (excepting only the <hi>Antitrinitarians</hi>) as hath been lately obſerved; and therefore this Miniſter is herein a Non-Conformiſt to all <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Churches, as well as to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and they are all Condemned together, as practiſing a point of <hi>Popery,</hi> in damning all that differ from them. Let us ſee now the Reaſon upon which all Proteſtant Churches are condemned by him. <hi>One Article</hi> (ſays he) <hi>of that Creed is about the Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt, from the Father and the Son, which the Greek Churches did not believe nor receive;</hi> and ſuppoſing them in an Error, he adds, <hi>I muſt be very bold if I leap into the Throne of Judgment, and pronounce them damned.</hi> I am as much afraid as he is, of inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Chriſt's Tribunal, and pronouncing any one damned, much more a whole Church, and ſuch a Church as comprehends ſo many Millions of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>But, 1. The Differences between the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Church, about the Article of <hi>Proceſſion,</hi> is by<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Field <hi>of the Church,</hi> lib. 3. c. 1. Loads Conf. <hi>p.</hi> 16. Pearſon <hi>on the Creed, p.</hi> 324.</note> 
               <hi>Learned men</hi> affirmed, to be only verbal, becauſe <hi>the</hi> Greeks <hi>acknowledged under another Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Expreſſion in the ſame thing, which the</hi> Latines <hi>underſtand by Proceſſion,</hi> viz. <hi>that the Spirit is of, or from the Son, as he is of and from the Father; That as the Son is God of God, by being of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo the Holy Ghoſt is God of God, by being of the Father and the Son, as receiving that infinite and eternal Eſſence from them both;</hi> Thus Biſhop <hi>Pearſon</hi> upon the Article, and if ſo it be, then there is no difference about the Doctrine it ſelf, but only about the word <hi>Proceſſion.</hi> But ſays this Miniſter, <hi>The Proceſſion of the Holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ghoſt is a moſt profound Myſtery, and very much obſcured by bringing in word Proceſſion;</hi> and is not this a moſt profound Objection? Is it not rather profound Non Senſe, to ſay, that the <hi>Proceſſion</hi> is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured by the word <hi>Proceſſion?</hi> And how does the expreſſing that Myſtery by <hi>Proceſſion</hi> any more obſcure it, than the infinite Dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God is obſcured by calling it <hi>Eternity?</hi> But, <hi>the Scripture on that occaſion never uſes the word.</hi> In relation to the Father, it is uſed<note n="*" place="margin">John 15.26.</note> expreſly, and in Relation to the Son, it is contained vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually in Scripture, where the Holy Ghoſt is often ſaid to be <hi>the Spirit of the Son,</hi> and that is all which is underſtood by proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him: and if no words are to be admitted, that are not found in Scripture, (the old-Subterſuge of the <hi>Arrians</hi>) we muſt not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29975:11"/>only exterminate <hi>Homoonſios, Proceſſion,</hi> and eternal <hi>Generation,</hi> but we muſt burn all our Bibles, except the Greek and Hebrew, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not properly the Word of God, but Words that ſignifie by the Agreement of Men; and if the original Words of Scripture may be Tranſlated by Words of humane Inſtitution, why may not a Doctrine of Scripture be ſo expreſſed alſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as many of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> have abſolved the <hi>Greeks</hi> from damnable Error in this Point, ſo it is notorious, that the Writers of our Church have always vindicated them from it; and therefore it cannot be imagined, that our <hi>Church</hi> in this <hi>Creed</hi> ſhould pronounce them damn'd; and it muſt be manifeſt injuſtice to put ſuch Interpretations upon the <hi>Creeds</hi> of a <hi>Church,</hi> as have heen ever diſclaimed by the chiefeſt Writers of it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Theſe damnatory Clauſes muſt be underſtood to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer only to the Belief of the Doctrines contained in the <hi>Creed,</hi> and not to every particular Word and Expreſſion in it. The great Fundamental Doctrine, which in this <hi>Creel</hi> is called the <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> is this, <hi>That we worſhip one God in Trinity, and Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> and of this Faith it is declared, That they who keep it not, <hi>ſhall periſh everlaſtingly.</hi> And they who believe this, <hi>viz. That the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, are Three Perſons and me God,</hi> do believe all that follows in the <hi>Creed,</hi> which contains nothing, but what is Eſſential to the Unity and Diſtinction of the Three Perſons, and therefore however, they who believe the <hi>Trinity,</hi> may ſcruple ſome Words and Expreſſions in this <hi>Creed,</hi> or underſtand nothing of them; yet as long as they believe the Doctrines, they are not included in the Sentence of <hi>periſhing everlaſtingly.</hi> Faith belongs not unto Words but Things, and though no one ſhall be damn'd for a Word, yet it is no uncharitableneſs to ſay after our Saviour, that <hi>he, who believeth not, ſhall be damn'd;</hi> neither is it any <hi>Popery</hi> to conclude, that if the Belief of the Trinity be neceſſary to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, it is neceſſary to Salvation; and if this <hi>Miniſter</hi> be of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mind, let him anſwer the Arguments that have been<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Sher. Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Doctrine of the Trinity.</note> lately urged for the neceſſity of that Belief; and let him alſo ſatisfie the World, if he can, why the <hi>Athanaſian Creed,</hi> which the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians appointed to be read in Churches, in their Directory drawn up at the <hi>Savoy, an.</hi> 1661, ſhould be afterwards a Reaſon of their <hi>Nonconformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he goes on with his Scruples about the Matter of Conſent, and declines to <hi>ſpeak of the Ceremonies, the Croſs, the Surplice,</hi> and behold the Reaſon, <hi>becauſe all know they came from</hi> Rome, <hi>and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29975:12"/>when</hi> Rome <hi>falls, they will fall too.</hi> This is an Art full of Venome, to traduce by odious Inſinuations, that which cannot be oppoſed by juſt Objections. It appears from<note n="*" place="margin">Orig. in Pſ. 38. Hom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Origen</hi> and others, that the <hi>Croſs in Baptiſm,</hi> and from<note n="†" place="margin">See <hi>Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> lib. <hi>5.</hi> rect. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and S. <hi>Jerome,</hi> that ſuch a Garment as the <hi>Surplice,</hi> were of Ancient Uſage; their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity is far enough beyond <hi>Popery,</hi> and they come no more from <hi>Rome,</hi> than do our <hi>Creeds</hi> and our <hi>Bibles;</hi> and if this Miniſter hath had a Revelation in his <hi>Patmos, that they ſhall fall with</hi> Rome, we are foretold, that in the laſt Times falſe Prophets ſhall ariſe, and muſt not take his Dream for Viſion. Next, <hi>en paſſant,</hi> he up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braids us with our praying for King <hi>James,</hi> a profeſt Papiſt, <hi>that he might perſevere in the Faith,</hi> but there is no ſuch Prayer in our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy; and if there were, ſeeing the Papiſts are Chriſtians, and believe all that is neceſſary to Salvation, (for I hope, <hi>he will not leap into the Throne of Judgement, and pronounce them damn'd,</hi>) why may we not pray for their Perſeverance in the Faith, not the Faith of a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> but the Faith of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that will ſuffice to ſave them. And now, after theſe little Skirmiſhes, we enter into the Battel, and muſt encounter the Reaſons which he has muſtered up againſt reading the <hi>impoſed Form of Common Prayer.</hi> And here pray judge between the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the Nonconformiſts.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he affirms, that <hi>during the Apoſtles Times, and two or three Hundred Years after, there was no Liturgy uſed nor impoſed, neither did they direct for the drawing up of any, and inforcing it by Penal Laws.</hi> Here are many things jumbled together, which muſt be ſeparated, Penal Laws; impoſing ſet Forms; Directions for them by the Apoſtles; and the Primitive uſe of them. As for Penal Laws, the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> themſelves allow them, and their <hi>Directory</hi> is as accountable for them as our <hi>Liturgy;</hi> impoſing to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered hereafter; and as to Directions for compoſing Forms, out of many that are urged, I ſhall ſelect theſe three Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Seeing there is convincing<note n="*" place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi>'s <hi>View of the Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory; Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> on <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichyus,</hi> p. <hi>83.</hi> Dr. <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> Vol. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>158.</hi> and Dr. <hi>Comber</hi>'s <hi>Scholaſtical Hiſtory,</hi> p. <hi>3.</hi> the Examiner of Dr. <hi>Combet,</hi> p. <hi>4.</hi> does queſtion the Solidity of their Proofs, but yet declines to undertake them.</note> Evidence, that the <hi>Jewiſh Church</hi> had a fixed Liturgy, and therefore both our Saviour, and his Apoſtles, who frequented their <hi>Synagogues,</hi> did certainly joyn in it, and not one <hi>Iota</hi> is to be found in the Goſpel that condemns it; from this Silence, and that Practice, we may certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the uſe of fixed Liturgies is lawful; that the joyning in them is warranted by their Example; and that ſeparation from a Church upon that account is abſolutely unlawful.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:29975:12"/>
            <p n="2">2. Our Saviour himſelf compoſed a Form of Prayer, for his Diſciples, and in ſo doing hath<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See M.</hi> Mede <hi>on</hi> Matt. 6 9.</note> commended a ſet Form of Prayer unto His Church; He enjoyn'd them, when they prayed, to ſay, <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. which is as plain a Preſcription of a Form as any Words can expreſs. It is<note n="†" place="margin">Clark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<hi>'s</hi> Diſc. conc. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies. <hi>p.</hi> 3.</note> confeſſed that this Form was anciently uſed in the Church, and this Primitive Uſe may be very reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly aſcribed to that Preſcription, eſpecially when we have ſo plain a Teſtimony as that of<note n="*" place="margin">Tert. de Orat. <hi>ca.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian, Novis Diſcipulis Chriſtus novam Orationis Formam determinavit; i. e. Chriſt</hi> hath preſcribed a new Form of Prayer to his new Diſciples: And therefore from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, nay from the Uſe of that Prayer which is confeſſedly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, we may certainly conclude, that a Form of Prayer is lawful in it ſelf; that it is uſeful and edifying, that a Prayor is not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unlawful or inexpedient becauſe it is a Form; and that the Preſcription, or Uſe of a Form in a Church, will not juſtifie ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. All the <hi>Directions</hi> which our Saviour or His Apoſtles have given for the Performance of the Duty of Prayer, may be apply'd to <hi>Forms</hi> of Prayer; ſuppoſe a Prayer to be exactly compoſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thoſe Directions, may not ſuch a Prayer be frequently uſed? Does it ceaſe to be made according to thoſe Directions if it becomes a Form? Is a good Prayer ſpoyled by uſing it often? And can the ſame Prayer be agreeable and not agreeable to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though it is not altered? The Spirit has given Directions for Prayer, and thoſe are equally applicable to Prayers compoſed by private Men, and to thoſe that are made for the uſe of a Church by the Governors of it; he hath given no Direction that private or <hi>extemporate</hi> Prayer ſhould be only uſed in the Church. The Rules are general, and if the Apoſtles have not directed the draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up Forms, they have left no Directions for any Prayer at all, ſeeing every Prayer either is, or may be a Form.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As to the Uſe of Liturgies in the firſt Ages of the Church he affirms, <hi>That it hath been abundantly cleared by thoſe that have laboured in this Controverſie, that the Paſtors of Churches in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Times did not read Prayers.</hi> Thoſe <hi>Labourers</hi> he refers to, are only Mr. <hi>Clarkſon,</hi> for out of his <hi>Diſcourſe of Liturgies</hi> he has extracted his Objections, and they are all anſwered already in Dr. <hi>Comber's Scholaſtical Hiſtory;</hi> but becauſe he has rallied up ſome few of them to defend his Nonconformity it is neceſſary to oppoſe the ſame Anſwers to them. He ſays, it is abundantly cleared, that the Primitive Paſtors did not read Prayers. Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> indeed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29975:13"/>affirms, that <hi>no ſuch Phraſe is to be met with in any Writers of the Four of five firſt Ages at leaſt;</hi> And to this it is replyed<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Comber<hi>'s</hi> Schol. Hiſt. pt. 2d. <hi>p.</hi> 206, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> that no ſuch Phraſe as <hi>extempore Prayer,</hi> nor any thing Equivalent can be produced in that time; that if written Forms of Prayer be clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved in thoſe Ages, ſuch poſitive Evidence cannot be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by a negative Argument, and the want of a Phraſe will not prove that any thing that was not which is proved to have been: That Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> himſelf hath found written Forms with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that time; and that it is certain, that the <hi>Jews</hi> had written Forms, and yet the reading them is is no where mentioned in Scripture. The <hi>Miniſter</hi> proceeds and urges, <hi>that Act.</hi> 12.5. <hi>the Prayer for</hi> Peter's <hi>Enlargement was</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>inſtant, forvent without ceaſing, but not by any Form, as is agreed on all ſides;</hi> as if Prayer by a Form could not be inſtant and ſervent; but the antient Church were of another opinion, when the <hi>Litany</hi> was common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed by<note n="*" place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Comber</hi> on the Lita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, earneſt or ſervent Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications. However, tho it be granted, that no ſet Form was uſed on ſuch an extraordinary occaſion, does it follow that none was therefore uſed in the ordinary Prayers of the Church? Or ſuppoſe that no Forms were uſed when the Church had the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt to direct their Prayer; does it follow, that no Forms are to be uſed, when that Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is long ſince ceaſed? if it does, then it follows alſo, that ſtudying Languages is now unlawful, becauſe the Apoſtles were taught them by Inſpiration, and that no Preacher ought to predmeditate or write his Sermons, becauſe we never read that the Apoſtles did ſo.</p>
            <p>But the next Objection he thinks to be demonſtrative, <hi>ſome</hi> ſays he, <hi>have been ſo curious as to obſerve, that in the Primitive times, the Saints uſually prayed with their Eyes fixed on the Mercy-Seat, or cloſed, which utterly diſables Perſons from reading Prayers.</hi> Mr.<note n="*" place="margin">On Pſal. <hi>132.7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mede</hi> has proved, that the <hi>Jews</hi> worſhiped towards the <hi>Ark,</hi> (whoſe cover was the Mercy Seat) and that the ancient Chriſtians worſhiped towards the Holy Table or <hi>Altar,</hi> which Anſwers to the Mercy Seat in the Jewiſh Temple; but whether their Eyes were fixed or cloſed is a <hi>moot Point</hi> to me, and I have not the <hi>Curioſity</hi> to make a reſearch in to it. Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> Labours to prove that they <hi>lift up their Eyes towards Heaven;</hi> but however, they diſpoſed of their Eyes, I hope the officiating Miniſter might nevertheleſs read Prayers to them. In out own <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> ſome devout Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may be ſeen with their Eyes cloſed, others looking towards
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29975:13"/>the <hi>Altar,</hi> and others towards Heaven, and even the <hi>Miniſter</hi> himſelf does often lift up his Eyes in Prayer; but I hope all this is no Argument that we have no Liturgy in our Church, and that they who ſcruple its uſe, do ſcruple nothing, and if it is no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment now, it never was one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We come next to his Second Claſs of Reaſons, which he thus begins, <hi>The Paſtors of Churches in the Primitive times, were under the teaching of the Anointing, and had the Spirit and Gift of Prayer.</hi> Suppoſe we this to be true, that they were taught to pray by the Unction of the Spirit; was this Unction extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, as the Gifts of Languages, Prophecying and Miracles? or was it an ordinary ſtanding Gift, which was to continue in the Church unto the end of the World? If he means the former, to what purpoſe does he urge a Gift which no one now can juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretend to? if the later, why did he not explain the Nature of it, and ſhew the Promiſe, the extent and the neceſſity of it, and withal anſwer the Arguments,<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Falk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Eccleſ.</hi> his Vindication of Liturgies, and the Caſes Conc. the Lawfulneſs of joyning with Forms of Prayer, <hi>part. 1.</hi>
               </note> that have been urg'd againſt theſe Pretences.</p>
            <p>But whatever he means by this Gift of Prayer, he would prove the uſe of it from <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> the<note n="*" place="margin">Juſtius Apol. 2. <hi>p.</hi> 98.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the former, he ſays, <hi>is Vindicated beyond all Exceptian.</hi> The Objectors underſtand by that Phraſe, that the chief Miniſter uſed his own Abilities in compoſing a Prayer. But<note n="*" place="margin">Libe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tas Eccleſ. <hi>p.</hi> 113. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Schol. Hiſt. <hi>p.</hi> 33. &amp; part. 1.</note> others think that it ſignifies his praying with all his might, <hi>i. e.</hi> with the utmoſt intention and fervency of Spirit. They explain this Phraſe by another of the ſame Author uſed a little before it, where he ſays, that <hi>they made their common Prayers to God</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, i. e. fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and importunately. They further prove, that the ſame Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in another place of <hi>Juſtin</hi> (where he repreſents the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in general, as praiſing God with Prayers and Thankſgivings, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) muſt ſignifie only fervency of Devotion, ſince it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be pretended that every Chriſtian in the Congregation pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed publickly by his own Ability and Compoſure; and laſtly they ſhew, that this Phraſe is by the antient Writers applied to ſinging of Hymns, which were ſet Forms of Prayers and Praiſes, and not Compoſed at every meeting by the Miniſter; and theſe are plain Demonſtrations, that this Expreſſion is no Proof of any Gift in praying, ſince it often ſignifies only fervency in it. The
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29975:14"/>
               <note place="margin">P. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Examiner of Dr.</hi> Comber labours much to vindicate this Phraſe, and he cannot deny, that it ſometimes ſignifies only fervency of Spirit when it is appled to the People, but he thinks it a very plain Caſe, that <hi>a Miniſter cannot properly be ſaid to pray to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of his Ability, when he doth not pray to the utmoſt of his Ablity;</hi> and may not the ſame thing be ſaid of the People alſo? If the Miniſter uſe a Form, may he not likewiſe pray <hi>with all his might,</hi> or as well as he is <hi>able?</hi> and is not this a plain Equivocating upon the word <hi>Ability?</hi> take it firſt for fervency, and then for a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of compoſing, and the Contradiction is ſolved, and the Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy Tranſparent.</p>
            <p>The other Proof is out of<note place="margin">Tert. Apol. cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian, ſine Monitore quia de pectore oramus,</hi> we pray without a <hi>Monitor,</hi> becauſe we pray out of the Heart. But this can be no Proof againſt a Form of Prayer; ſor 1. They who joyn with a Miniſter that prays <hi>Extempore,</hi> do pray as much with a <hi>Monitor,</hi> and have a Prayer dictated to them as much, as if they joyned in a preſcribed Liturgy. And 2. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Heart,<note place="margin">Schol. Hiſt. part. 1. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p.</hi> 46. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> may ſignifie either ſaying a Prayer by Heart; or ſecret mental Prayer without words; or praying hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, ſincerely and affectionately, <hi>de anima innocenti, de Spiritis Sancto,</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> a little after) with a prayer proceeding from an innocent Soul, and the Holy Spirit moving and exciting it Theſe interpretations are probable and conſiſtent with the uſe of Liturgies, and conſequently from this paſſage no Argument can be drawn againſt them: Yet from thence this Miniſter takes oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to vent his Malice againſt Liturgies, and to reproach them, as <hi>an heatheniſh way of Praying.</hi> Now if our Saviour preſcribed a <hi>Form</hi> to his Diſciples, (and it is impoſſible for him to prove the the contray) then this reproach is Blaſphemy; might not an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> ſay as well, <hi>That Prayer it ſelf is an Heatheniſh practice,</hi> or a <hi>Quieteſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Comment. in <hi>Entychi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> p. <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>taht vocal Prayer is a Heatheniſh way of praying.</hi> Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> thought it probable that the Heathens learnt to uſe ſet Forms from the Example of the Jewiſh Church, and he cites Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities to prove it, and<note place="margin">View of the <hi>Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</hi>
               </note> Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> produces out of <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Alexander, ab Alex.</hi> theſe two Reaſons of that practice, which he thinks may paſs Chriſtian, <hi>leaſt evil things ſhould be asked in ſtead of good,</hi> and <hi>leaſt any thing ſhould be ſaid Prepoſterouſly in their Prayers;</hi> and therefore the practice of the <hi>Heathens</hi> is ſo far from being a prejudice to Liturgies, that it is a ſolid Argument for them, Whether either, or both, the Example of Gods Church, or the Catholick reaſon of mankind were the Original of it, the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29975:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>univerſal uſe of them among <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> is an impregnable Proof of their expediency, and can be aſcribed to no other cauſe, but the voice of God or Nature.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He tranſcribes this Objection after Mr. <hi>Clarkſon, when the</hi> Chriſtians <hi>were ſo numerous in</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>that it was thought neceſſaryto diſpoſe of them in ſeveral Churche, the Emperour</hi> Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine<note place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſt. lib. 4. c. 35.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to</hi> Euſebius <hi>for</hi> 50 <hi>Bibles, for the uſe of thoſe Churches, but there is no mention of any one common Prayer Book. Euſebius</hi> commends <hi>Conſtantine</hi> for obſerving in his Court the manner of the publick Service in the Church, he firſt imoplyed his mind in the Meditation of the Scriptures, and then with thoſe who dwelt in his Palace he repeated,<note place="margin">Ibid cap. 17.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the authorized Prayers; and it is known, that he himſelf compoſed a Prayer which he<note place="margin">Ibid cap. 19, 20.</note> preſcribed to his Army. And after ſuch convincing, Proofs can a Negative Argument be thought conſiderable enough to Ballance them. Is it imaginable that <hi>Euſebius</hi> intended to give an exact <hi>Inventory</hi> of all that was provided for thoſe Churches? <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſends to <hi>Euſebius</hi> in <hi>Palaſtine</hi> for 50 Bibles, probably becauſe the beſt Copies might be there moſt eaſily procured; does it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow, that no prayer Books were provided at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where it was eaſie to procure them? and if we ſhould ſend to <hi>Holland</hi> for Bibles when we want them, would it not be as plain a Demonſtration, that we have no prayer Books in <hi>England?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sue Schol. Hiſt part. 2d. <hi>p.</hi> 48. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> He pretends, <hi>That when Forms of Prayer began to be uſed, ever Church made uſe of what Forms they pleaſed,</hi> and for this he cites <hi>Socrates Scholaſ. lib.</hi> 5. the paſſage he intends is in <hi>Chap.</hi> 22. In which the Hiſtorian reflecting upon a diviſion among the <hi>Novatians</hi> about the time of keeping <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and ſhewing that antiently in different Churches, it was obſerved at different times without breach of Communion, does paſs from thence to obſerve the diverſity of other different uſages in the <hi>Chriſtan Chruches,</hi> as the different Cuſtoms of keeping the Faſts before <hi>Eaſter,</hi> the Marriages of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and the different Rites and times of Prayer, and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting Scripture in many Provinces and Countreys. The he tells us, that the <hi>Novations</hi> in the <hi>Holleſpont</hi> did not obſerve the ſame manner of praying with thoſe of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, that <hi>upon the whole every where, and in all the Worſhips</hi> (or Rites) <hi>of Prayers, you cannot find, that they agree together, two in the ſame thing;</hi> and this is the paſſage they inſiſt on. But 1. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, may ſignifie Ceremonies and Rites of Prayer, for of different Ceremonies he was before Diſcourſing, and then
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29975:15"/>the Paſſage will be no proof of different Forms. 2. Admitting that he ſpeaks of different Prayers, this diverſity is not ſpoken of ſingle Congregations, but of ſeveral Nations and Dioceſes, ſuch as, for inſtance, <hi>Jeruſalem, Cyprus, Conſtantinople.</hi> 3. A little after we have the reaſon fo this variety, <hi>I judge,</hi> ſays <hi>Socrates, that the Biſhops, who preſided in ſeveral Gages, were the cauſe of it;</hi> and how? <hi>They tranſmitted their own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage as a Law to thoſe who ſhould come after them;</hi> thus the cauſe of this diverſity was not Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, but Law and Preſcription. 4. Immediately after, he vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicates the <hi>Nicene Council,</hi> which had determined the Controverſie about <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and preſcribed a certain time to keep it. But diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity in praying, and the different times of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> are by this <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian</hi> propoſed as things alike indifferent; and if Church Authority may determine and preſcribe in one caſe, ſo it may alſo in the other. Thus we have the great Example of the <hi>Nicene Fathers</hi> for preſcribing, and in ſtead of the <hi>Liberty</hi> they pretend to, the <hi>Preſcription</hi> of ſet Forms, or Rights of Prayer to whole Dioceſes and Nations. In ſhort, the deſign of the Hiſtorian is to ſhew, that there were divers <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> in the Church in Things indifferent, and that the Communion of the Church ought not to be divided for them: Now <hi>Cuſtom</hi> is a Law, introduced by Practice; and Law is a reſtraint upon Liberty: And if indifferent things may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> they may be preſcribed by <hi>Canons,</hi> and Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for them is alike unlawful.</p>
            <p>He obſerves further, that <hi>there were ſeveral Liturgies allowed even in the Roman Communion, and that this Branch of the Churches Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty was taken away by the</hi> Council of Trent, <hi>and here in</hi> England <hi>by the</hi> Reformation. And what was that <hi>Liberty</hi> which was thus abridged? Not an Arbitrary <hi>Liberty</hi> in every <hi>Paſtor</hi> of a Pariſh to uſe what Form he pleaſed, but the uſe of different Rules of Prayer that were before preſcribed and practiced in different National Churches and Dioceſes. The different Offices in <hi>England,</hi> as thoſe for inſtance after the uſe of <hi>Sarum</hi> and <hi>York,</hi> did agree in <hi>Subſtance,</hi> they had the ſame Forms of Prayer, and differed for the moſt part in <hi>Rubricks</hi> and <hi>Ritualities</hi> only; and when our firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed an <hi>uniform Order,</hi> it was not eſteemed an Encroachment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſtian Liberty; neither are Unity, Order and Uniformity, the leſs valuable becauſe Councils and Popes were for them</p>
            <p n="5">5. His next Reaſon is an <hi>Invective</hi> againſt the Introducers of <hi>Liturgies,</hi> and in the midſt of it he defines <hi>ex Cathedrd, That the Liturgies which bear the great Names of S.</hi> James, Peter, Mark,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29975:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Baſil <hi>and</hi> Chryſoſtome <hi>are known Forgeries.</hi> That they are ent rely genuine as they are now extant, is affirmed by no one; but that they are Forgeries quite throughout, and eſpecially the Liturgy aſcribed to St. <hi>James,</hi> is ſo far from being known, that we may ſafely affirm, that it is impoſſible to know it: And the contrary opinion of ſo Learned men, as<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Falk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, <hi>p.</hi> 149.</note> 
               <hi>Baronius, Ddurantus, Leo, Allatius, Sixtus Senenſis, Poſſevinus, Pamelius,</hi> and others among the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts; Dr. <hi>Hammond, Thorudike, Falkner, Caſaubon, Salmotius, Durel,</hi> and ſome other Proteſtants will bear me out in affirming it.</p>
            <p>But behold the Modeſty, Charity and Humility of this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; <hi>'Twas the Ignorance, Carnality, Sloth and Lazineſs of the Clergy, together with their Pride which firſt brought in and impoſed Service-Books on the Churches — When the Church began to be an Harlot, when Biſhops were not Silver Trumpets, but tinkling Cymbals, &amp;c. when in Councils, as of</hi> Epheſus <hi>and</hi> Chalcedon, <hi>they profeſt they did</hi> literas ignorare, <hi>and could not write their own Names to confirm their Canons, then came in our Liturgies.</hi> Thus far <hi>the Son of Thunder,</hi> but I take heart again, for find it is <hi>brutum fulmen,</hi> and our <hi>Prayer-Books</hi> are in no danger from it. The Falſhood and weakneſs of this <hi>Raillery</hi> is<note place="margin">Schol. Hiſt. part. 2d. <hi>p.</hi> 276.</note> ſufficiently expoſed already, and it is impoſſible ſuch ſtuff ſhould impoſe upon any, but the greateſt <hi>Bigots</hi> of Fanaticiſm. Ignorance, Carnality, Pride and Lazineſs brought in Liturgies; he might as well have ſaid, that <hi>Burglary</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> did introduce them; if Pride and Ignorance brought in Liturgies, why are they not read in <hi>Conventicles?</hi> for<note place="margin">In his Cure of Diviſions.</note> Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> hath complained to all the World, that the People who fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent them, <hi>for their Ignorance, Injudiciouſneſs, Pride and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceitedneſs are their Grief and their Shaine,</hi> and certainly we may believe him. But if Pride and Ignorance brought in Litugies; we remember well then <hi>Entbuſiaſm, Sacriledge</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> did <hi>eject</hi> them. We have<note place="margin">Preface to Dr. <hi>Still.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> had convincing Proofs, that the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> firſt brought <hi>extempore</hi> Prayers into <hi>England;</hi> thoſe <hi>Miſſionaries of Antichriſtian</hi> were the firſt Teachers of them; and when Presbyterian Miniſters were <hi>Trumpets</hi> to Rebellion, when their Sermons and their Arms brought the <hi>beſt of Kings</hi> to the Scaffold, when the Church was rent in pieces with damnable Doctrines, when <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roham</hi>'s <hi>Prieſts</hi> profaned the Pulpits and the Altars, when the Stalls and the Shambles were the chief Schools of the Prophets, when all Religion was vaniſhed into Cant; and Blaſphemy and Nonſenſe were entitled to the Holy Spirit; then were <hi>Liturgies</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29975:16"/>firſt aboliſhed, and <hi>extempore Prayers</hi> firſt univerſally practiſed in any Chriſtian Nation in the World.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Liturgies,</hi> he ſays, were brought in when the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be an Harlot. <hi>Smectymnius</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Anſwer to <hi>Remonſt.</hi> p. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> derived their Pedigree from Three Canons of the <hi>Laodicean, Carthaginian,</hi> and <hi>Milevitan</hi> Councils; and thus they are allowed to be in uſe about 1300 years ſince, and has the Church been a <hi>Whore</hi> for ſo many Ages? has ſhe forſaken her <hi>Spouſe</hi> ſo long? has ſhe renounced <hi>Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> for 13 Centuries together? Yes, and much longer too, when we diſpute about Epiſcopacy; for when we come to that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, the Myſtery of iniquity was working even in the times of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> and the Church did then begin to be an Harlot alſo; ſo little do ſome men care how they wound our common Chriſtianity, and condemn the whole <hi>Catholick</hi> Church of Chriſt, ſo they may but vent their Malice againſt <hi>Liturgies</hi> and <hi>Biſhops.</hi> But becauſe he cannot deny that <hi>Liturgies</hi> were introduced in the 4th and 5th <hi>Centuries,</hi> he particularly Rallies upon the Ignorance of the Biſhops of thoſe Ages. And were thoſe ever reputed igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Ages? when was the Church better enlightned with Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than when <hi>Chryſoſtome, Baſil, Nyſſene, Nahianhen, Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> the two <hi>Cyrills, Lactantius, Ambroſe, Jerome, Auguſtine, Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore Peluſ. Theodoret, Vincentius, Gennadius,</hi> and many others were the Luminaries of it. But among theſe <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> even the <hi>Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks,</hi> and the Women have been thought more able <hi>Divines</hi> than the <hi>Fathers;</hi> and indeed if Ability is to be meaſured by the <hi>Gift of Prayer,</hi> as they call it, they may vye Learning even with their own Teachers; for their moſt ignorant Zealots do often pray with as much fluency of words, with as much pretence to the Spirit, (and which is the main Gift) with as much Confidence, as the <hi>ableſt Miniſters</hi> among them. But the Biſhops of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Chalcedon</hi> could not write their Names, and Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> indeed produces the <hi>Subſcriptions</hi> of Three or four to prove it. And to<note n="*" place="margin">Schol. Hiſt. pt. 2. <hi>p.</hi> 300.</note> this it is replied, That thoſe Subſcriptions are of no credit as being ſuſpected of Forgery; but ſuppoſe there were four Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops among 830 in thoſe Councils, who were ſo illiterate, is it not a very impudent Calumny to ſay indefinitely, as he does, <hi>That the Biſhops of</hi> Epheſus <hi>and</hi> Chalcedon <hi>could not write their Names to confirm their Canons?</hi> might it not as well be ſaid, that the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> were <hi>Independants,</hi> becauſe there were Five of that <hi>Sect</hi> among them, or that the <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts Miniſters</hi> of this Age, have generally died as <hi>Traitors,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29975:16"/>Two or three were executed for being in <hi>Monmouths</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</p>
            <p>His laſt Reaſon concerns the impoſing of Liturgies; and here he denies not the Lawfulneſs of them, but after he has begged the belief of his Followers, <hi>That they were not uſed in the Primitive times for many Hundred of years,</hi> he pretends to prove the unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of impoſing them. Now one would think it a very plain Caſe, <hi>that things lawful in themſelves may be lawfully enjoyned by lawful Authority;</hi> but this <hi>Miniſter</hi> is of another opinion, and the only Reaſon he gives for the unlawfulneſs of preſcribing Forms is this, <hi>That it is a reſtraint upon the Gifts of ſuch Miniſters, as have Ability to compoſe better Prayers themſelves</hi> and this he illuſtrates by the trite inſtances <hi>of Treſpaſs Offering, and of a Law obliging thoſe, who are not Lame and Impotent to make uſe of Crutches.</hi> But, 1. All this is impertinent to the Diſpute before us; for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters in our Church are not reſtrained from the Exerciſe of their own Abilities in publick Prayers; they may uſe their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Prayers in the Pulpit, and the <hi>Fifty fifth Canon,</hi> as explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the general Practiſe, is an allowance of it, and therefore if the Exerciſe of <hi>Abilities</hi> be not excluded in our Church, the pretence of <hi>reſtraint</hi> can never juſtifie a Separation from it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Objection is grounded on theſe falſe <hi>Suppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> that God is better ſerved by conceived Prayers, than by a publick Liturgy; that the Church is leſs difyed by it; that it is unlawful to lay a reſtraint upon private Gifts; and that it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to ſeparate for better Edification; and unleſs all theſe <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions</hi> here precariouſly ſuppoſed to be true, (and I think he will find it impoſſible to prove them) then his whole reaſoning, and the <hi>Crutches,</hi> he has brought to prop it, and the <hi>Pidgeons, Lambs</hi> and <hi>Bullocks</hi> which attend it, are plainly unſerviceable to him. His <hi>Pidgeons</hi> and <hi>Crutches</hi> are deſigned to intimate that a <hi>Form</hi> of Prayer is a cheap, impotent, unedifying way of Worſhip, in Compariſon of their <hi>extempore</hi> Effuſions; but this he ſhould have proved; for he knows we aſſert the contrary; we think that Prayers are not more acceptable, becauſe they are <hi>inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> or of private Compoſure; that the <hi>Framers</hi> of our Liturgy were as well gifted as <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> that the Church may be better edifyed by the Spirit of the <hi>Church,</hi> than by the Spirit of a <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;</hi> and that thoſe Prayers are fitteſt for the <hi>People,</hi> which they are before acquainted with, and wherein they are ſecured from Preſumption and Impertinence, Blaſphemy and Nonſenſe.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:29975:17"/>
            <p>He ſhould have proved likewiſe, that the Exerciſe of private Gifts cannot lawfully be reſtrained by publick Authority; we know, that even the miraculous Gifts of the Spirit were ſubject to reſtraint, and we have an expreſs Rule, <hi>That the Spirit of the Prophets muſt be ſubject to the Prophets:</hi> There is no Law, no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor Revelation againſt ſuch a reſtraint; on the contrary both Reaſon and Religion do require, that the uſe of private <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> be regulated by publick <hi>Order,</hi> and that the vain Oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them be reſtrained.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 87. ad Prot. Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Calvin</hi> has expreſly declared for the neceſſity of preſcribing Forms, <hi>To remedy the ſimplicity and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfulneſs of ſome, to teſtifie the Conſent of all the Churches in the ſame Prayers, and to prevent the deſultory Lightneſs of thoſe, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Novelty;</hi> In ſhort, all the <hi>Foreign reformed Churches,</hi> do either uſe or approve of preſcribed Liturgies; the old <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways allowed them, and even the <hi>Presbyterian Directory</hi> preſcribed every thing but Words; and if private Spirits may be reſtrained to Senſe and Matter, why not to Form and Language alſo?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Admitting that ſuch reſtraint is unlawful, and that conceived Prayers are more edifying than Forms, he ſhould then have proved, that it is lawful to ſeparate for <hi>better Edification.</hi> The antient <hi>Puritans</hi> thought otherwiſe, and ſo did the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Aſſembly</hi> in their Controverſie with the <hi>Independents;</hi>
               <note place="margin">See <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>pt. 1.</hi>
               </note> and ſo both Reaſon, Experience, and Revelation do convince us, that the reſtraint of private Gifts will not juſtifie the dividing of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> that the ſilenceing an able <hi>Miniſter</hi> is not ſo miſchievous as <hi>Schiſm;</hi> that the Pretences of better <hi>Edification</hi> is the fruitful Parent of endleſs <hi>Separations,</hi> and that the Church <hi>(which is in the Houſe of the living God)</hi> cannot be built or edified, by being torn in pieces and deſtroyed? Thus have I conſidered at large his <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> about Liturgies, it is the principal Fort and Bulwark of his Cauſe, and the ſlight defences which remain will be eaſily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Point that follows next, is the abjuring of <hi>the ſolemn League and Covenant, as in it ſelf an unlawful Oath, and impoſed on the Subjects of the Realm, againſt the known Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom.</hi> And is it not extreamly modeſt in theſe Men, to Quarrel at the State, for requiring them to renounce an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious and Rebellious <hi>Covenant?</hi> was it reaſonable to admit ſuch men into the Offices of the Church, as were ſworn and obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolved to extirpate the whole Government of it? But let us conſider the Reaſons which he urges againſt the abjurating that Covenant.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:29975:17"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>There are many learned Preachers that never redd a Law Rook, they know nothing of</hi> Manna Charta, Bracton, Littleton, Cook, <hi>Common Law or Statute Law—is it reaſonable then to require them, to declare the Covenant is contrary to known Laws and Liberties, which they are utterly unacquainted with?</hi> Indeed there is no neceſſity that a good Preacher ſhould be an able Lawyer; and much leſs is it neceſſary to read over a Lawyers Library, to be convinced, that the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was illegal, can none but profound Lawyers know that <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony</hi> and <hi>Burglary</hi> are againſt our Laws and Liberties? Does not every ſenſible man know, that the impofit on of an Oath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Law to warrant it, is contrary to it and that nothing is Law, which has not the concurrence of <hi>King, Lords and Commons</hi> to enact it? have theſe Miniſters never heard of the<note n="*" place="margin">3 Car. 1. c. 1. S. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> which declares all others without Law to be againſt our Laws and Liberties? Or can they tell us by what Law the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> was eſtabliſhed? was it not impoſed without the Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the <hi>King.</hi> and againſt his expreſs Command? had they never heard of the Oaths and Laws about the <hi>Kings Supremacy?</hi> and is not the<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cad Oxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienſis de ſolrum Freder. <hi>p.</hi> 8. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Cotenant</hi> plainly Contradictory to it? and Laſtly, do they not know that this <hi>Abjuration</hi> is required by an <hi>Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament?</hi> and what need then of conſulting Law Books about a <hi>Covenant,</hi> for which there is no <hi>Preſident</hi> in them, when the Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlative Power it ſelf has declared the unlawfulneſs of it? it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt this <hi>Ignorance</hi> is affected; time was, when they were ſo well acquainted with Laws and Liberties, that they preached the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple into a Rebellion for them; in the Covenant it ſelf they ſwore expreſly<note n="*" place="margin">Artic. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to preſerve the Priviledges of Parliament, and the Liberties of the Kingdom;</hi> if <hi>then</hi> they knew thoſe <hi>Liberties,</hi> can they <hi>now</hi> be unacquainted with them? or is it not as lawful to abjure, as to ſwear, without knowledge. Article 1. They ſwore to preſerve <hi>the Religion of the Church of</hi> Scotland <hi>in Doctrine, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Diſcipline and Government;</hi> and was there one in a Thouſand of the <hi>Covenanters</hi> that had a competent knowledge of theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars? How could it be imagined, that he common People ſhould know them? and yet they never ſcrupled to exhort them to take it, tho they were morally certain, they did not underſtand it. And Laſtly, why is not this Objection <hi>now</hi> conſidered by the <hi>Virgin Daughter of</hi> Scotland, as he Phraſes it: There they force the Clergy to ſwear that <hi>W.</hi> and <hi>M.</hi> are lawful <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Queen</hi> by <hi>Laws</hi> of that Kingdom, and is this reaſonable, when they are ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unacquainted with thoſe Laws, and many Learned Preachers
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:29975:18"/>have never read the <hi>Civil</hi> not <hi>Statute Law,</hi> nor <hi>Craig</hi> nor <hi>Skine,</hi> nor the <hi>Original Contract;</hi> but it is always to be obſerved, that the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> never do condemn what they do not practice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Subſtance of his next Reaſon is this, <hi>That the Covenant was taken by the People of Two or three Kingdoms, and a man had need be a good.</hi> Caſuiſt, <hi>that can declare underſtandingly, that no one man is bound by that Oath, which almoſt every man took.</hi> Now I believe this <hi>Covenant</hi> was not taken by the Majority of theſe Kingdoms; in <hi>England</hi> I am ſure it was generally refuſed by the Clergy, the Univerſities and the greateſt part of the Nobility and Gentry. But admit the Majority took it, the force of his Reaſon depends upon this Propoſition; <hi>That an Oath taken by a vaſt munitude muſt needs be Obligatory;</hi> and is it neceſſary to read all the <hi>Caſni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Books of Divinity</hi> to confute ſo manifeſt a Falſhood? in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Countries many Millions do take Monaſtick Vows, and all the Clergy ſwear obedience to the Pope; and may not an ordinary Caſuiſt <hi>declare underſtandingly,</hi> that none of them are bound by thoſe Vows and Oaths which <hi>all of them have taken?</hi> The <hi>Holy League</hi> in <hi>France</hi> was ſworn by more than the <hi>Solemn League</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> was it therefore Obligatory? and is it not a ſufficient <hi>Humiliation</hi> to which this Miniſter has <hi>called</hi> me, to be bound to anſwer ſuch Abſurdities.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He urges, that <hi>by the Covenant all Perſons were bound in their places to endeavour a Reformation of the Church according to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and the Examples of the beſt reformed Churches,</hi> and he asks, <hi>is this an unlawful Oath?</hi> I anſwer, the Queſtion is deceitful; a man hinds himſelf by Oath <hi>to ſerve God and the Devil,</hi> and he asks, is it not lawful to ſerve God? <hi>is this an unlawful Oath?</hi> Thus the Covenanters did ſwear to endeavour <hi>Reformation,</hi> Art. 1. and to extirpate <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> Art. 2. But this Miniſter mentions <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> only, and then impertinently demands, is this Oath unlawful? I am ready to maintain againſt him, that an Oath to ſerve the Devil is not more unlawful, than an Oath to deſtroy <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> and that upon this ground, becauſe it is of <hi>Apoſtolical Inſtitution.</hi> There are many other things unlawful in that Covenant, (as any one may be ſatisfied by the unanſwerable Reaſons of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> againſt it) and therefore if this <hi>Miniſter</hi> will prove it lawful, let him juſtifie it throughout, and not fly to ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, as may ſerve to juſtifie the moſt execrable Oaths that can be, by producing one ſingle Paſſage, that may ſeem juſtifiable in them. But thus he proceeds, <hi>If a man ſhould ſwear, that in his Place
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:29975:18"/>and Calling he would endeavour to caſt every Idol out of the World:</hi> and what is the conſequence of this terrible <hi>If?</hi> Why, truly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all; but he filly adds, that in <hi>Scotland</hi> they have <hi>caſt off Prelacy, and eſtabliſhed Presbytery, i. e.</hi> they have caſt out the <hi>Idol,</hi> and ſet up the <hi>true God</hi> among them; but if this be his meaning, that Epiſcopacy is <hi>Idolatry,</hi> I account of him as one of the incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Fanatical Roul,</hi> that call every thing <hi>Idol</hi> or <hi>Antichriſt</hi> that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſes them, and I am not obliged to anſwer Bigotry and Frenzy.</p>
            <p>The laſt <hi>Point</hi> he inſiſts on, is a Paſſage out of the <hi>Commination Office</hi> in the Liturgy, wherein the Church declares her Deſire, that <hi>the Godly Diſcipline, uſed in the Primitive Church, may be again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored;</hi> and ſays, <hi>it is much to be wiſhed for.</hi> It is wonderful to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what work he makes with this Paſſage! but I am willing to believe he never read it in the Liturgy. It was long ſince an old conceit of the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Hooker, <hi>p.</hi> 331.</note> that the <hi>Primitive Diſcipline,</hi> which was ſo much wiſhed for by the Compilers of our Liturgy, was the <hi>Presbyterian Diſcipline,</hi> and from them, I preſume, he borrowed the Objection. But in the Liturgy it ſelf there is no Foundation for it, as will appear from a view of the Paſſage it ſelf in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Commination; <hi>Brethren, in the Primitive Church, there was a Godly Diſcipline, that at the beginning of</hi> Lent, <hi>ſuch Perſons as ſtood convicted of Notorious Sins, were put to open Penance, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in this World— In ſtead whereof, (until the ſaid Diſcipline may be reſtored again, which is much to be wiſhed for,) it is thought good,</hi> &amp;c. and is Presbytery the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> here deſired? undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly as much as <hi>Popery</hi> or <hi>Mahumetaniſm;</hi> It not that <hi>Diſcipline</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly declared to be the Diſcipline of publick Penance, which in the ancient Church was inflicted upon ſuch as ſtood convicted of Notorious Sins at the beginning of <hi>Lent,</hi> in order to their Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Admiſſion to the Holy Sacrament at <hi>Eaſter?</hi> What can be more expreſs and evident, than that the Ancient <hi>Leut Diſcipline</hi> is there alone intended? And have the Non conformiſts, as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends, <hi>ever written</hi> for, preached for, and ſuffered for, the Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this Diſcipline? Have they ever wiſh'd or deſired it? Have they not always written and preach'd againſt it? Do they not ſtill exclaim at it, as Popery and Superſtition? But this Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter pronounces conſidently, that <hi>this Expreſſion ſtands in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, as well for the Juſtification of the Nonconformiſts, as for a Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt the Prelates.</hi> Thus the <hi>Godly Diſcipline</hi> is a Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them who have always deſired it, and Juſtification to them who have always oppoſed it; and if Nonconformiſts muſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:29975:19"/>needs be juſtified by Blunder and Contradiction, this Miniſter I confeſs is a fit Apologiſt for them. But behold the Reflections he makes on this Paſſage.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Reformers and Compilers of this Book of</hi> Common Prayer <hi>had no full Satisfaction with what was then done.</hi> What, Were they not fully ſatisfied with the Liturgy? The firſt Liturgy of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th was applauded by the whole<note n="*" place="margin">2, 3 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. c. 1.</note> Parliament, <hi>as compoſed by the Special Aid of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> Tom. 3. p. 171.</note> Doctor <hi>Taylor</hi> the Martyr publickly declared, that the whole Church-Service in King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi>'s Second Liturgy, <hi>was ſo fully perfected according to the Rules of our Chriſtian Religion, that no Chriſtian Conſcience could be offended with any thing therein contained.</hi> The Papiſts were the only Perſons in thoſe Times, that were diſſatisfied with it, and therefore, in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days, a Challenge was made by<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. Tom. 3. p. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Cranmer,</hi> that with <hi>P. Martyr,</hi> and four or five more, <hi>they would enter the Liſts with any Papiſts living, and defend the</hi> Common Prayer <hi>Book to be perfectly agreeable to the Word of God, and the ſame, in effect, which had been for</hi> 1500 <hi>Years in the Church of Chriſt;</hi> and let any one now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, whether our firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> were not fully ſatisfied with the Liturgy. But he adds, <hi>they ingenuouſly confeſs, they came ſhort of the Primitive Diſcipline, and that the Reformation ſhould have been carried on higher, if the Times would have given leave.</hi> They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, they could not revive the ancient Diſcipline of <hi>Lent,</hi> and they deſired a higher Conformity to the Primitive Church, (not in relation to the Hierarchy and Liturgy, but) in the ſtrictneſs of Mens Lives, and the impartial ſeverity of publick Penance, <hi>Yet,</hi> ſays he, <hi>they had then their Government by Biſhops, Archbiſhops, Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, Archdeacons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as we have at this day.</hi> They had ſo, and were fully ſatisfied with it, and there were no Proteſtants in that Age that ſeparated from it. Archdeacon <hi>Philpot,</hi> Archbiſhop <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and ſeveral <hi>Biſhops,</hi> our firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> approved that Government, and lived and died in the Adminiſtration of it; they did not permit it only, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did Divorces to the Jews, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the hardneſs of their Hearts, (as this Miniſter does falſely inſinuate,) but they never intimated the leaſt Suſpition of its un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſs, and they plainly,<note n="*" place="margin">Preface to the Book of Ordin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> declared Epiſcopacy to be evidently founded upon Scripture and Apoſtolical Inſtitution. But theſe <hi>Reformers</hi> and <hi>Martyrs</hi> were ignorant of thoſe things which are now known unto Women and Artificers; poor Men! they were under a diſpenſation of Darkneſs, and the Goſpel-Light of Separation was totally hidden from them.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:29975:19"/>
            <p>Secondly, he obſerves, <hi>That it is more than 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>00 Years ſince theſe good Men recorded their Deſires of Reſtoring the ſaid Diſcipline; and is it enough</hi> (ſay he,) <hi>that the Church carries her good Wiſhes with her through all Generations</hi> Enough certainly, while the Reſtoring that Diſcipline is impoſſible: Our firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> could not revive it, becauſe the univerſal and incorrigible Wickedneſs of that Age, could not endure the Yoke of Primitive Penance and are ſcandalous Offenders now leſs numerous or loſs incorrigible? If the <hi>Reformers</hi> are excuſable, much more our preſent <hi>Governors,</hi> by how much the preſent Age is more untractable and more obſtinate againſt the Bands of <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> Is it poſſible now to reduce Offenders to the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Humiliations, the Faſtings and Watchings, the Sackcloth and Aſhes the Proſtration at the Church Doors, and the other Auſterities of Ancient Penance? Will any of the <hi>Diſſenter's</hi> ſubmit to this Diſcipline as a ſatis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faction for their Schiſm? If ſuch an impracticable Diſcipline were impoſed, theſe Miniſters would preſently cry out <hi>Popery</hi> encourage all Offenders to oppoſe it, and ſet open the Doors of their Conventicles to receive them ſuch an Impoſition would be vain and pernicious, it would ſcandalize the weak, and alienate the obſtinate, and ſerve only to empty our Churches, and crowd the Conventicles; and though for that reaſon they may deſire it. yet the Church is not obliged to preſcribe a Remedy, that will make the Phyſician contemptible, and the Patient incurable. The reſtoring of that Salutary Diſcipline (as the reviving of Primitive Piety,) may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways wiſh'd for, but perhaps will never be attained; but the licentious Wickedneſs of the preſent Times, the general Contempt of all the Cenſure of the Church, and the manifold Schiſms with which it is rent in pieces, do make it now impoſſible; and if it were eſtabliſhed, it is not to be hoped, that the obſtinacy of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> would be ſubdued, nor their Averſion to the Church be reconciled by it.</p>
            <p>I intend not to follow this Miniſter through his tedious Digreſſion about <hi>Reformation,</hi> and much leſs to ramble with him as far as the <hi>Temple</hi> at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> to which, forſaking his Text and his Purpoſe, he undertakes a Pilgrimage, and returns with theſe wiſe Obſervations,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>That the Temple was built upon</hi> Ornan<hi>'s Barn; that this</hi> Ornan <hi>was of Princely deſcent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had a Princely Mind; and that Temple-Work is hard Work, 'tis Threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Thus, after a long Journey, <hi>he brings back nothing, but Apes and Peacocks</hi> as himſelf obſerves of ſome who ramble into the <hi>Indies.</hi> Theſe are the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Doctrines for which this <hi>Threſher</hi> is admitted by his Hearers; and ſince a <hi>Barn</hi> is his Delight, may he never <hi>Threſh</hi> in the Houſes of GOD, nor profane thoſe Sanctuaries that are conſecrated to his Worſhip.</p>
            <p>But I return to <hi>Reformation,</hi> and in Anſwer to his Harrangue about it I deſire it may be remembred, 1. That this Miniſter does not ſeek the ſame Reformation which was ſought by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, for <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery</hi> is not the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> neither is Extirpation of <hi>Biſhops</hi> the Propagation of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> 2 Reformation is very good in it ſelf and the <hi>Churchmen</hi> are for it much more than the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> but they cannot be convinced that the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:29975:20"/>removing Decency, Order, and an Apoſtolical Government, is Reformation; they know, that this is the uſual Vizard to diſguiſe Sacrilege, Avarice and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and that the Sectaries endeavour not to reform the Church, but to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it, that they <hi>may ſeize on its Inheritance;</hi> and withall they cannot but reflect upon the experience which we have had of <hi>Sectarian Reformation;</hi> when Prelatical Government was reformed into no Government, and a ſober Liturgy into Enthuſiaſm, and 39 Articles into infinite Hereſies, that could ſcarce be pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell'd in all the ancient Catalogues, and in ſtead of the Power of Godlineſs, there enſued ſuch an Inundation of Wickedneſs, as no Age could parallel. This was obſerved by the<note n="*" place="margin">For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, by <hi>Edwards</hi> in his <hi>Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graina.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Presbyterians</hi> themſelves, and an ingenious <hi>Foreigner</hi> who then reſided at <hi>London,</hi> made this Obſervation upon thoſe Times,<note n="*" place="margin">A Letter of a Noble Venetian to Ca. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barino,</hi> Tranſlated and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>1648.</hi> p. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>one of the Fruits,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of this Bleſſed Parliament, and of theſe two Sectaries, (Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians and Independants,) is, that they have made more Atheiſts, than I think there are in all Europe beſides;</hi> and if we judge of the Tree by its Fruits, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee no more ſuch Reformations, have they reaſon to blame us for it?</p>
            <p n="3">3. It ſhould be conſidered, that no pretence of <hi>Reformation</hi> can juſtifie Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from a Church, in which no ſinful Terms of Communion are impoſed. There is no Church in the World, which is free from all Corruptions in Doctrine, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Diſcipline, or Manners, and if the want of ſome Reformation be a juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for Renouncing Communion, the Unity of the Church is nothing but a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and it will be lawful for every Man to ſeparate from all the Churches in the World, for it is only the Triumphant Church in Heaven, which is perfectly <hi>without ſpot and blemiſh.</hi> Defect of Diſcipline, and purer Communion, were the pretences of the <hi>Donatiſt</hi> and <hi>Novatian</hi> Schiſms; but they were condemn'd by the Catholick Church, and<note n="*" place="margin">Aug. con. Parmen. Epiſ. lib. 2, 3. Tom. 7.</note> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> proves at large againſt the Donatiſts, that Corruption in Diſcipline or Manners cannot make the Communion of ſuch a Church ſinful, nor juſtifie Separation; and hence any one may diſcern, how impertinent to this purpoſe are all this Miniſters Clamours about <hi>Reformation;</hi> for though the purſuit of it may be commeadable, and the Church may need it, yet it is evident his <hi>Nonconformity</hi> and <hi>Separation</hi> cannot be juſtified by it, for there is no Church upon Earth, which needs not Reformation, and if Men may ſeparate where they ſee any thing amiſs, this Principle will carry them to a Separation from all Chriſtian-Society, and that is a plain Demonſtration of the Faiſhood of it.</p>
            <p>I have now conſidered and weigh'd all his Pleas for Nonconformity, and having found them light and deceitful in the Ballance, having ſufficiently prov'd them to be falſe and fallacious; I conclude, that the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted <hi>for Righteouſneſs ſake,</hi> and that his<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 24.</note> virulent Reproaches of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Prophetick</hi> Language are no better than <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> and a contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prophanation of Gods word, by making it the Inſtrument of his Spite and Animoſity.</p>
            <p>And one Reſſection more will make it yet more evident, that they did not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for Righteouſneſs; it is this, that tho his Pleas be allowed to have Truth and Reaſon in them, yet they will not juſtifie the Diſſenters Separation. Every one knows that theſe Miniſters were not puniſhed for not conforming as <hi>Miniſters,</hi> but for ſetting up <hi>Conventicles;</hi> tho they could not Act as publick Miniſters, yet they might have adher'd to the Communion of the Church, and then they would have been in no danger of Perſecution; they ſuffered for their Separation, and if all this Miniſters Objections will not juſtifie it, they will not juſtifie their Sufferings for it. The Plea of Reformation I have ſhewn already to be inſufficient; and it is evident that <hi>Lay Diſſenters</hi> are unconcerned in all the others; they were neither ablig'd to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:29975:20"/>renounce the Covenant, nor the Lawfulneſs of Reſiſtance, nor the Ordination of Presbyters, nor to declare their Aſſent and Conſent to the Common-prayer; and this Miniſter himſelf denies not the Lawfulneſs of their joyning in it. Thus he hath left all his Congregation without any defence, and it remains that they ſuffered not for <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> but for an unrighteous and indefenſible <hi>Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us ſee whether the ſame Objections will juſtifie his own <hi>Separation?</hi> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Oath of <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> to be unlawful, was that a term of our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion? was it required of all that come to our Prayers or Sacraments? and might he not have adhered to the Communion of our Church without ſwearing or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring it? be it granted next that <hi>Reordination</hi> is unlawful to be comply'd with; was that likewiſe any term of Communion in Worſhip and Sacraments? And if they could not Preach as <hi>Miniſters,</hi> could they not Communicate as <hi>Laymen?</hi> and is the unlawful ſilencing of a <hi>Miniſter</hi> to be revenged with <hi>Schiſin?</hi> The next point is the uſe of the <hi>Liturgy;</hi> and is there any thing unlawful in all our Prayers? if he cannot Conſent to ſome Paſſages in the <hi>Rubrick,</hi> or in a <hi>Creed</hi> that is very Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom recited, yet there is nothing ſinful in our ordinary Worſhip, and the <hi>occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Communion</hi> allow'd by the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> themſelves is a clear Confeſſion of it: And Laſtly, as to the <hi>Covenant,</hi> if it muſt not be renounced, cannot they worſhip God in our Churches without renouncing it? or does it at all oblige them to <hi>Separation?</hi> Mr.<note n="*" place="margin">Defence of Cure, p. <hi>68.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baxter</hi> has prov'd, that the <hi>Covenant</hi> binds them to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with our Church, becauſe, <hi>it binds to Reformation according to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the beſt reformed Churches; but all reformed Churches in</hi> Chriſtendom <hi>do commonly profeſs to hold Communion with the Engliſh Churches in the Liturgy; if they come amongſt us where it is uſed; therefore</hi> (ſays he) <hi>it ſeems to me to be Perjury and Covenant breaking to refuſe Communion with the Churches that uſe the Liturgy, as a thing meerly on that Account unlawful.</hi> Thus Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> and theſe Conceſſions are very remarkable; that <hi>Separation</hi> on the Account of our <hi>Liturgy</hi> is unlawful; that it is a breach of their <hi>Covenant;</hi> and is condemned by all <hi>Reformed Churches;</hi> and what new <hi>Pleas</hi> can this Miniſter produce to defend his Separation?</p>
            <p>Will he urge the Pretence of neceſſity <hi>to Preach the Goſpel,</hi> and that therefore he was forced to ſeparate, becauſe he could not do it in our Churches? But if he was under the ſame neceſſity the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> was, then he has ſurely the Commiſſion and Authority of an <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> but if he hath no Commiſſion from God, (let me uſe the words of an antient<note n="*" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fard</hi> cited in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par. p. <hi>80.</hi>
               </note> Nonconformiſt) <hi>it is the Devil that hath ſent him forward to Preach</hi> againſt the Authority of the Church, and the Prohibition of the Chriſtian <hi>Magiſtrate.</hi> In ſhort, they have neither the ſame <hi>Commiſſion</hi> as the Apoſtles; neither is there the ſame <hi>neceſſity</hi> of their Preaching, for the Goſpel is now planted in this Kingdom; it is Preached in our Churches and it would not be extinguiſhed if this Miniſter and his Brethren (to uſe his own Seraphical Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) were all them <hi>Dumb Dogs,</hi> or <hi>Breaſts without Milk,</hi> or <hi>Bells without Clappers.</hi> And withal it is here to be obſerved, that it is evidently proved,<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid p. <hi>1.</hi> ſect. <hi>8, 9, 10, 11,</hi> &amp; <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> that according to the Doctrine of the moſt learned <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> of former times, both their <hi>Separating</hi> and their <hi>Preaching</hi> are abſolutely unlawful.</p>
            <p>The Sum of all is this; the Laws againſt the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> were made for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> the Execution of them was not ſo cruel, as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; their perſecuting of the <hi>Government</hi> did extort it; the Presbyterians themſelves have always condemned <hi>Toleration;</hi> they do ever perſecute whenever they have Power; this Miniſter declaims only againſt Perſecution <hi>for the Truth;</hi> but all his Pretences to <hi>Truth</hi> appear to be falſe and groundleſs; and if they were admitted, would not juſtifie <hi>Separation;</hi> and therefore the reſult is this; That his <hi>Call to Humiliation</hi> is an unreaſonable Clamour, and that it ought to have
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:29975:21"/>been directed to the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> themſelves, and eſpecially to their <hi>Miniſters;</hi> who have been the moſt grievous <hi>Perſecutors;</hi> who have crubified <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> by dividing hith; have torn his Body into pieces; have ſeparated from the whole <hi>Catholick Church;</hi> under pretence of Reforming the Reformed Religion have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached and weaken'd it, have been always undermining that Church which is the Bulwark of it; have bound themſelves by impious Oaths, and very lately ebtred into an Alliance with the Papiſts, to deſtroy it: And laſtly, have ſuffered obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately for an Unrighteous Chuſe, condemned by Reaſon and Revelation, by the Univerſal Church of all Ages, and by all the Reformed Churches in the World.</p>
            <p>Having now Anſwer'd the whole Deſign if this <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> and all that looks like Argument in it; it would be ſuperfluous to examine the <hi>Remainder</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect particularly on his malicious Hints and Intimations, his Cant and Shtyr, his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of Scripture, his Uſes and his Prayers, which he Recommends to his People, and wherein he Feaches them that Vile and <hi>Diviliſh</hi> Practice of turning <hi>Prayers</hi> into <hi>Libels,</hi> and inſtructs them to Pray much worſe than the <hi>Phariſee;</hi> to commend themſelves to God<note n="†" place="margin">See p. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>As followers of the Lamb and the Lords Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> and to accuſe the Church-men before him, <hi>as Dumb Dogs and Wolves, and bloudy Perſecutors.</hi> Thus do they fill up the meaſure of their Fathers, who ſin their Prayers taught the People <hi>to Speak evil of Dignities,</hi> and to Curſe the beſt of <hi>Kings,</hi> as a Bloudy, Perſecuting, obdurate <hi>Tyrant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I cannot but take notice of his inſolent, Triumph for the Eſtabliſhment of Presbytery in <hi>Scotland. Now,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is fulfilled that which was ſpoken by the Prophet, The Land of</hi> Zebulun, &amp;c. — <hi>The People which ſate in Darkneſs ſaw great Light, and to them which ſat in the Region and Shadow of Death, Light is ſprung up.</hi> And was this Prophecy never fulfilled till now? It <hi>Presbytery</hi> the <hi>Meſſias</hi> whoſe Light is there foretold? Did <hi>Nailor</hi> himſelf ever utter more Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Blaſphemy? Has the <hi>Virgin Daughter of</hi> Scotland proclaim'd a new <hi>Goſpel</hi> which was not Preach'd before? Is it the <hi>Evangelium Armatum,</hi> or the <hi>Goſpel of</hi> Xaverius, or of the <hi>Whore of</hi> Babylon? Hither to I thought that Epiſcopal Churches might have the Light of the Goſpel; but a new Light hath now diſcovered that they are all in Darkneſs, and that all Chriſtian Churches for 1500 Years together, have been in the Regions of Death, without Chriſt, without the Light of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and conſequently without Salvation.</p>
            <p>One thing more I muſt obſerve, that the Sermons and Writings of theſe <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> do make it <hi>as clear as the Sun,</hi> that all the projects of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nïon</hi> with that Party are abſolutely impracticable. The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are the only <hi>Diſſenters</hi> that are thought capable of Comprehenſion; but to take <hi>them</hi> into our Church, we muſt caſt out our Liturgy, and our Biſhops, we muſt ſubmit our Necks to the Iron Yoke of Presbytery; in ſhort we muſt deſtroy our Church if we will have an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with them; no <hi>Alterations</hi> will content them; they who have, &amp; they who have not taken the <hi>Covenant</hi> do think themſelves bound to extirpate Prelacy, and to Reform according to the model of <hi>Scotland,</hi> they deſire no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and deſpiſe it; when Treaties of Peace are propoſed <hi>they make themſelves ready to Battel;</hi> their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility is Irreconcileable, and the total Deſtruction of our Church is the ſum of all their Endeavours and Deſigns.</p>
            <p>But Oh! That our Lives were as good as our Religion, and our Manners pure and primitive as the Conſtitution of our Church; for then would God <hi>cover is under his Wings,</hi> and he that <hi>hath deliver'd, and doth deliver,</hi> would ſtill <hi>deliver us.</hi> Our <hi>Church,</hi> we know, <hi>is Founded on a Rock,</hi> let us <hi>depart from Iniquity,</hi> and her <hi>Foundation</hi> ſhall ſtand ſure, and the <hi>Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29975:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
